本故事取材于真实犯罪档案
1969年7月4日 加州 瓦列霍市
你去哪了? 我从七点等到现在
Where have you been? I've been waiting since 7:00.
我去买烟火 上车吧
Get in I had to find fireworks.
让我来开 快上车 我一整天没吃东西了
Let me drive Get in I haven't eaten in 24 hours.
你到底来不来?
Are you coming or not?
艾德餐馆
整个下星期在圣雷法第四街 1017号的钢索里珠宝店
直到星期五都营业至九点
这里人太多了
It's too crowded.
你不是很饿吗?
I thought you were starving.
我们去安静一点的地方
Let's go someplace quiet.
好吧
Okay.
我们来这里干嘛?
What are we doing?
坐着 听听音乐 聊聊天
Sitting Listening to music Talking.
你有点怪怪的 你还好吧? 没事 很好啊
You seem weird Is everything okay? Yeah, everything's fine.
七月天耶 干嘛穿这么多?
It's July How many shirts are you wearing?
我会冷 都美国国庆日了你还会冷?
I'm cold You're cold on the Fourth of July?
去死吧!
Fuck off and die!
干嘛?" 去死吧"?
What?" Fuck off and die"?
别糗我
Shut up.
那辆车有在露天戏院吗?
Was that car at the drive in?
我在艾德餐馆有看到这辆车
I saw that car at Mr. Ed's.
要我叫他开走吗? 留在车里
Do you want me to tell him to leave? Stay in the car.
那是你老公吗? 不是
Was that your husband? No.
黛玲 那是谁?
Who was that, Darlene?
不要担心
Don't worry about it.
别叫我不要担心 到底是谁? 没事啦
Don't tell me not to worry Who was it? It's nothing.
糟了!
Oh, shit.
快走吧
Let's go.
快走啊 小黛!
Now, D.
证件拿出来
Get your wallet.
老兄 你差点吓死我们
Man, you really creeped us out.
瓦列霍警局 我要举报一起双尸命案
Vallejo Police Department I want to report a double murder.
你的姓名 地点
May I have your name and where you are calling...
哥伦布省道往东一英里的停车场
If you go one mile east on Columbus Parkway
一辆咖啡色车上有两具尸体
a public park, you'll find kids in a brown car.
他们被九毫米鲁格手枪射杀
They were shot with a 9mm Luger.
去年那两个小鬼也是我杀的
I also killed those kids last year.
再见
Goodbye.
四星期后 加州 旧金山
吐出来
Spit.
快点 儿子
Come on, buddy.
我吞下去了 为什么?
I swallowed it Why?
因为是薄荷口味
It was minty.
不可以这样 对身体不好
You can't do that It's not good for you.
午餐盒别忘了
Lunch box.
为什么不让我搭校车? 因为我们迟到了
Why am I not going on the bus? Because we're late.
听着 晚上你住妈妈和艾伦那里
Okay, you're staying with your mom and Aaron tonight.
你不喜欢有个新弟弟?
So, you don't like having a new little brother?
不喜欢 很诚实
No, not really Oh, that's honest.
认真学习
Learn a lot.
十二宫杀手
晚上我会考你喔
There will be a test tonight!
十点以前到曼尼的店 行动要快!
重建街64号 在山丘上与86街的交叉口
旧金山纪事报
早安
Morning.
很好 你今天早啊! 早安
Hi Good morning.
大家早安 早安
Morning Morning.
提醒你明天是申请截止的期限
第十五届青年摇滚大赛
申请表可以在湾区 各学校和图书馆索取
矮子 今天的咖啡如何?
How's the coffee today, Shorty?
咖啡夭寿好喝!
编辑部
两分钟后开编辑部会议
Editorial in two.
旧金山纪事报 请速交编辑部
大家早安 早安
Good morning, gentlemen Good morning Good morning.
史坦登 告诉浩尔先生 那篇兵役委员会的报导棒极了
Well, Stanton, tell Mr. Howe the draft board piece was damn near perfect.
葛雷史密斯先生
Mr. Graysmith.
不行 不行
Horrid Horrid.
尚可接受
Not so horrid.
就用这张尚可接受的吧
Horrid I'm thinking we go with not so horrid.
保罗 社会版有什么?
Paul, what's on the crime beat?
洁妮丝在大家脱光光之前 就离开瑞士小火锅派对
Janice in Datebook left the fondue party before everyone got naked.
的确是个重罪
That's a crime.
不是盖的 你们见过她吗?
Have you seen her? Wouldn't kid you.
她会引起一连串犯罪事件
It may be the beginning of a crime wave.
你得看看这个
You need to see this.
去把发行人找来
Go get the publisher.
亲爱的编辑
"Dear Editor
我去年圣诞节在赫曼河
"This is the murderer" of the two teenagers last Christmas at Lake Herman
和七月四日在瓦列霍附近 谋杀两名青少年
"and the girl on the Fourth of July near the golf course in Vallejo.
为了证明我杀了他们
"To prove I killed them
我将举出只有警方和我自己 才知道的细节
"I shall state some facts which only I and the police know.
圣诞节 超小口径子弹
"Christmas, brand name of ammo, Super X.
一共射出十枪
"Ten shots were fired.
男孩倒在地上 双脚伸直
"The boy was on his back with his feet to the car.
女孩
"The girl..."
麻烦你接着念
Would you read that, please?
女孩向右倒 双脚朝西
"The girl was on her right side, feet to the west.
七月四日 一位女孩穿着花纹套装
"Fourth of July" One, girl was wearing patterned slacks.
男孩膝盖也中弹 子弹品牌是韦斯顿
"The boy was also shot in the knee" Brand name of ammo was Western.
附上部分的密码
"Here is part of a cipher.
其余的两份密码 分别寄给了 瓦列霍时报 以及 旧金山观察家报 的编辑
"The other two parts of this cipher are being mailed to the editors of" the Vallejo Times and S.F Examiner.
我要你将密码刊于贵报头版
"I want you to print this cipher on the front page of your paper.
密码将揭露我的身分
"In this cipher is my identity.
如果八月一日星期五前没登出
"If you do not print this cipher by the afternoon of Fry"
我就会大开杀戒
F R Y," First of Aug '69 I will go on a kill rampage Fry night.
我整个周末都会猎杀落单的路人
"I will cruise around all weekend killing lone people in the night
直到我凑齐了一打尸体为止
"then move on to kill again" until I end up with a dozen people over the weekend."
没有属名 只有一个记号
It's unsigned except for a symbol.
看起来像是枪的瞄准器
Is it me, or does that look like a gunsight?
今天就是八月一日 他要我们刊在今天的晚报
Today's August first He wants his code in the afternoon edition.
旧金山观察家报 没种刊登 我们就拿到湾区的独家报导
If the Examiner doesn't have the balls to run it, we scoop the Bay.
这家伙扬言要杀害12人 不刊登 他就会犯案
Al, this man is talking about shooting 12 people And not running this might make him do that.
刊登了就会创下危险的先例
If we run it, we might be setting a very dangerous precedent.
拜托 这很有新闻爆点
Oh, come on, now, it's newsworthy.
那大众又将怎么看待我们报社
Well, giving some sick bastard a soapbox, what does that say to people?
等等 我们知道这谋杀案是真的吗?
Back up Is this Vallejo story true? Do we know that?
保罗? 干嘛 要我采访瓦列霍案件吗?
Paul? What? I cover crime in Vallejo?
好吧 给我十分钟 拍下密码交给旧金山警局
Yeah, I cover crime in Vallejo Ten minutes Let's shoot the code and call SFPD.
假设这是真的 至少原稿在我们手上
If it turns out to be real, at least we'll have the material.
好吧
All right.
小葛 你不是还有漫画要画?
Graysmith, don't you have that cartoon to finish?
对喔
Oh, yeah.
我是 旧金山纪事报 记者 保罗·艾瑞
Hi, this is Paul Avery from the San Francisco Chronicle.
我有收到信 希望有人协助理清
I'm looking for someone to shed some light on a letter we received.
谢谢 穆拉斯警官
Thank you Sergeant Mulanax.
我是 旧金山纪事报 的保罗·艾瑞
Sergeant, Paul Avery from the San Francisco Chronicle.
贵警局是否有未破解的枪击命案
I just wanted to check if you had an unsolved firearm related homicide
发生于圣诞节或七月四日?
on Christmas and maybe one on July fourth.
妈的 你们也收到了吗?
Shit You guys got one, too?
有了 瓦列霍警方证实了枪杀案
Confirmed VPD, they confirmed the shootings.
艾尔打给 观察家报 他们收到不同密码的信
Al's on the phone with the Examiner They got the same letter with a different code.
所以 瓦列霍时报 圣诞节 两名青少年被发现陈尸情人巷
So did Times Herald Christmas, two teenagers on lover's lane Both DOA.
大卫·法瑞戴以及贝蒂·珍森
David Faraday and Betty Jensen.
七月四日 黛琳·费伦和麦克·梅
July fourth, Darlene Ferrin and Michael...
我想是梅休 他没死 她挂了 凶枪呢?
I think it's" Mayhew." Anyway, he lived, she didn't The murder weapons?
弹道检验符合信上提到的细节
Ballistics, everything he said in the letters matched.
我猜 瓦列霍时报 会刊登
I mean, I think the Times Herald's gonna go with it.
观察家报 要登 但不是头版
The Examiner's going, but won't go front page.
我说我们应该上头版 他要杀一打人也不是我们的错
I say let's go front page If he kills 12 people, it's not our fault.
罗伯 我们要那张漫画
Robert! We need the cartoon.
你还没画完? 我画完了啦 凯萝
You're not finished? No, I'm finished, Carol I'm finished.
发行人还在这里
Thieriot's still here.
真的?
Really?
查尔斯 初版十分钟后印刷
The first edition is off the floor in 10 , Charles.
等我们一下
Give us a sec.
好 重新排版
Okay, re plate.
把它刊在...刊在第四页
We'll go on page... Page four.
悬赏20元给破解密码的人如何?
What do you say, 20 bucks whoever cracks the psycho's name?
他不会透露他的名字
He won't give his name.
摩迪酒吧? 谁要一起去?
Morti's? Anyone?
我要去 好吧
That's where I'm heading All right.
摩迪酒吧
课本放在书桌上 灯打开
Put those on my desk Turn on the light.
把你的书拿着
Grab your book.
解码专家 大卫·康著
去换睡衣
Now go get your jammies on.
好了 大家听着
All right, people, listen up.
密码划分成三区块 每区块有八行 十七个符号
The cipher's broken into three sections, each with eight lines and 17 symbols.
符号间没有空格划分字句
No breaks between the symbols denoting different words.
没有数字 任何线索代换
No numbers or clues to substitution keys.
符号至少有七种不同密码
And you got symbols from at least seven different sources.
希腊字母 摩斯密码 海军旗语 气象符号 占星记号
Greek, Morse code, Navy semaphore, weather symbols, astrological signs.
瓦列霍大屠杀虚惊一场
来看看这些密码 好
Hey, take a gander at this code thing Okay.
12小时后 加州 萨里纳斯 哈顿夫妻家早餐时刻
要试试看吗?
You wanna give it a go?
3天后 加州 旧金山
以前坐这里的是个好漫画家 鲍伯·巴斯恩
Guy who used to sit there was a great cartoonist Bob Bastian.
突然就跳槽到电视公司
Now he's doing public television For some reason.
保罗·艾瑞
Paul Avery.
罗伯·葛雷史密斯 我来九个月了
Robert Graysmith I've been here nine months.
你说对了 他没透露他的名字
You were right, by the way He didn't give his name.
谁破解的? 沙利纳斯市的历史老师和他老婆
Who cracked it? A history teacher and his wife in Salinas.
我热爱杀人因为很好玩
"I like killing people because it is so much fun.
比猎杀危险动物更有快感
"It is more fun than killing wild game in the forest
因为人类比任何猛兽更危险
"because man is the most dangerous animal of all to kill.
杀人过程让我感到兴奋
"Something gives me the most thrilling experience.
甚至比性爱高潮更有快感
"It is even better than getting your rocks off with a girl.
更棒的是当我死后
"The best part of it is that when I die
我会在天堂重生
"I will be reborn in paradise.
我杀死的人会成为我的奴隶
"And all that I have killed will become my slaves.
我不会公布我的名字 因为
"I will not give you my name because you will try to slow down
你们会阻碍我死后收藏奴隶
"or stop my collecting of slaves for my afterlife."
我认为这家伙头脑烧坏了
Methinks our friend's a tad bit fuckered in the head.
听说他还给了瓦列霍破码以提示
I heard he even sent Vallejo a code key, just to help.
底下那些是什么? 没意义的符号
What is that at the bottom? Leftovers.
或许是字谜
Maybe an anagram.
罗伯汉普
你怎么会猜字谜?
How does one do that?
我喜欢猜字谜 我常玩
I like puzzles I do them a lot.
嬉皮
你怎么知道他不会透露姓名?
How did you know he wasn't gonna give his name?
"危险动物"
Dangerous animal.
危险动物
危险动物? 怎么听起来很耳熟?
What dangerous animal? How do I know that?
保罗 是的 丹波顿
Paul Yes, Templeton.
要开编辑会议 好吧
Editorial, now Very well.
又来了一封信
Another letter.
内容差不多 描述杀人详细过程
More of the same Details about the murders.
他在枪上装上手电筒 所以才能在黑暗中行凶
He taped a flashlight to the gun That's how he hit them in the dark.
他还自封了一个名号
And he gave himself a name.
亲爱的编辑 我是黄道带
一个半月后 加州 那帕 1969年9月27日
你知道这里原本是蒙地舍罗镇?
You know this used to be the town of Montecello?
后来郡政府认为这块土地 改成一座湖比较有用
But at some point, the county decided that the land would work better as a lake.
所以就把它淹没了
So they flooded it.
一整座城镇  就这样沉在水底
But there's an entire... Hidden city under the water.
我们去年春天来过 记得吗? 对哦
We were here last spring, remember? Oh, yeah.
那里有个人 这是座公共公园啊
Somebody else is here It is a public park.
我觉得他在看我们
I think he's watching us.
因为我们很好看
Well, we're very good looking.
他到哪里去了?
Where'd he go?
躲在树后面 好 他只是在撒尿
He went behind that tree All right So he's taking a leak.
他走过来了
He's coming towards us.
老天 他手上有枪
Oh, my God, he has a gun.
别动
Don't move.
把钱和车钥匙交出来 没问题
I want your money and your car keys Okay.
我们不会反抗
We're not gonna do anything, okay?
会乖乖听话 告诉我们该怎么做
We're gonna cooperate Just tell me what you want us to do.
拿去
Here.
你可以拿走我所有的东西
You're welcome to everything I have.
还是我可以给你其它的东西
If there's anything else I could do for you...
好比说开张支票给你
Maybe I could write you a check?
我可以给你我的电话号码
Okay, I could give you my phone number.
或许我可以帮助你
You know, I might be able to help you.
我可以帮你很多忙 他主修社会学
Even more than you might think He's a sociology major.
其实我念法律系
Pre law, actually.
车钥匙 我不知道钥匙放哪里了
Oh, keys You know, I'm sorry, I don't know exactly where I put my keys.
可能在毯子底下 可以吗?
They might be on the blanket Is it okay if...
钥匙在这里
Here's the keys.
别站起来 我要她绑住你
Don't get up I want her to tie you up.
好吧
Okay.
他再靠近一点我可能抢得到枪
You know, if he comes any closer, I might be able to get that gun.
别想乱来 并没有
Don't get any ideas I'm not.
我从蒙大拿州越狱时杀了警卫
I killed a guard escaping from prison in Montana.
我不会乱来 好吗?
I'm not doing anything, okay?
我不怕多杀一个人
I'm not afraid to kill again.
别看我
Look away.
那所监狱叫什么名字?
What was the name of that prison?
你说监狱在蒙大拿州对吧?
Hey, you said it was in Montatana, right?
我要开走你的车去墨西哥
I'm taking your car I'm going to Mexico.
你绑住我们
We didn't complain when you tied our hands.
我们没抱怨
Okay, you have everything that I have.
你要什么我们也给了你
We have done everything that you've asked.
没事的 没事的
It's okay It's okay.
她没有绑紧你 对吧?
She tied you loose, didn't she?
躺下来让我绑住你的脚
Get on your stomach so I can tie your feet.
这里晚上很冷 我们会冻死
Okay It gets really cold out here at night We could freeze.
好了吗?
Okay, you all done?
有人会问我 枪有上膛吗?
You know, just because people are gonna ask, was that thing even loaded?
没事 一切都会没事
It's okay This is all gonna be okay.
43L2号警车前往南向奈斯谷街
Dispatch, this is 43L2, heading south on Knoxville Road.
找到一辆遗弃白色福克斯
I've got an abandoned white VW Karmann Ghia...
瓦列霍2 20 68 7 4 69 9 27 69 6:30刀杀
那帕市警察局
Napa Police Department.
我要举报一起命案
I want to report a murder No, a double murder.
是双尸命案
They are two miles north of park headquarters.
陈尸在公园内的白色福克斯汽车内
They were in a white Volkswagen Karmann Ghia.
人是我杀的
I'm the one that did it.
43L2警车发现男性被害人 救护车正前往现场
43L2 has a male victim with him Piner's ambulance has been dispatched.
一样 男的没死 女的挂了
Boy lived, the girl didn't Again.
老天 很难想像有幸存者
God, can you imagine surviving something like that?
瓦列霍两起凶杀案
Writing the dates on the side of the car.
那帕一起 为什么在那帕?
We got two Vallejo killings, now there's one in Napa Why Napa?
他为什么在瓦列霍以外的地方做案? 我的老天
What the hell is he doing out of Vallejo?
你在画什么?
Sweet mother of Christ, what are you drawing?
湖边的大学生 这是他描述黄道带的打扮
Kid at the lake This is what he said the Zodiac was wearing.
天呐 果然是怪里怪气的
God, that's a hell of a get up.
保罗 你在做什么? 海曼 我写完了
Paul, what are you doing? Hyman, I wrote it It's done.
我现在要把它打出来
Now I just got to type it up.
没打完不算 我们还要审稿
Type it up? It's not finished until you type it up We've got to read it.
那是什么? 湖边的黄道带
What's that? That's the Zodiac at the lake.
那小子是什么来头? 他怪怪的 好像嗑了药
What's the story with the kid? He seems a little touched or medicated or...
小葛吗? 他是乖乖牌
Graysmith? Yeah, what is it? He's a fucking boy scout.
不抽烟 不喝酒 不讲脏话
He doesn't smoke, he doesn't drink, he doesn't curse.
他回来了" 人类比任何猛兽更危险"
And he's back I knew it" Man is the most dangerous animal of all."
我听过这句话在 最危险的游戏 里
I knew that I heard that from somewhere The Most Dangerous Game.
某公爵把猎杀人类当运动的电影
It's a movie about a Count who hunts people for sport.
猎杀人类 最危险的游戏
People The Most Dangerous Game.
那是谁? 瑟若夫公爵
Who's that? That's Count Zaroff.
瑟若夫? 字头是Z?
Zaroff? With a" Z"?
这是新闻快报
And that will be all for the news on the 20.
以下的地区将进行宵禁
We've got curfews in effect tonight for the following counties
那帕 索拉诺 康特拉卡斯塔 阿拉米达 马林 圣马刁
Napa, Solano, Contra Costa, Alameda, Marin, and San Mateo.
两星期后 加州 旧金山 1969年10月11日
请大家注意自身安全
So please, everyone, stay safe.
旧金山的维克叩应 你不怕黄道带?
Vic in San Francisco, you're on the line You're not scared of the Zodiac?
谁会怕他 他只杀乡下小孩
Heck no, he's only shooting those farm kids.
我怕的是穿着奇装异服
What scares me is those hippies out in the Haight
只会乱搞杂交的嬉皮
with their free love and weird clothes.
来自华卡维尔市的艾菲瑞叩应
We've got Alfred from Vacaville.
刚才那位先生在做人身攻击 死者不只是乡下小孩
You know, I think that was really offensive It's not just farm kids.
他们是品行优良的年轻人
These are nice, clean cut young people.
没人贬低这些人的性命
Hey, nobody's downplaying the loss of human life here, Alfred.
上一个家伙就这么想
Well, that last guy was.
我们北湾是个优良的社区
We have good solid communities out here in the North Bay.
不像那些充斥撒旦崇拜者的城市
Unlike in the city where you have Satanists running around.
说得好 黄道带崇拜撒旦吗?
Well, you bring up a good question Is the Zodiac a Satanist?
奥克兰的安柏 你认为呢?
Amber from Oakland, what do you think?
不知道 不过印在报上的密码 不像是基督教符号
I don't really know, but I thought that code they printed didn't look very Christian.
我认为报社不该刊登
But I think the bigger problem is that the papers shouldn't have printed
任何关于黄道带做的事
anything that the Zodiac has been doing.
他们只是为了增加发行量
That they're just printing all that stuff to sell more newspapers.
不过黄道带也说不刊登的话 他就会杀更多人
Well, the Zodiac did demand they print his letters or he'd kill more people.
登不登他照样会杀人 至少我个人认为是这样
Yeah, but he would have done it anyway, whether they printed it or not, I think.
很有趣的观点 你认为接下来他会怎么做?
An interesting point So, what do you think he'll do next?
旧金山警局 有人在计程车里打架
San Francisco Police Department Yes There's a fight in a cab!
你在哪里?
What is your location?
华盛顿街3398号 樱桃街转角
3398 Washington, at the corner of Cherry.
有人喝醉了 他好像在抢劫
One's drunk and we think he's robbing him.
歹徒还在犯案吗? 是的 拜托你们快点
Is the crime still in progress? Yes, please hurry.
天呐 你看!
Oh, my God, look!
可恶!
Nuts!
不管你是谁 你欠我一座新台灯
Whoever this is, you owe me a new lamp.
计程车司机在普西迪区遭枪杀
Cabbie's been shot three blocks from the Presidio.
凶手又不是我 我老婆可以担保我整晚都陪着她
Well, it wasn't me I've been with my bride all night.
去煮咖啡
She can vouch Go put on the Folgers.
你会来接我?
You'll pick me up?
我先说你要赔我哪种台灯
Let me just describe the lamp you're gonna buy me.
我才刚上床耶 嫌犯是个黑人男性
I just got to sleep Suspect's Negro, male adult.
华特封锁现场 维持秩序
Walt's on scene, locked up the cab and secured the crowd.
说真的 我已经睡到手都麻了
Seriously, dead asleep I lost feeling in my arm and everything.
要吃饼干吗?
Crackers.
你吃过日本料理吗?
You ever try Japanese food?
什么意思 像是照烧吗? 不 像是生海胆?
What do you mean, like teriyaki? No, like the urchin.
生鱼片? 我正在吃东西耶
Raw fish I'm eating here, Bill.
我一直想试试看 那你为什么不试?
I always wanted to try it So, why don't you?
没时间
Haven't got around to it.
晚安两位 今晚真是笨贼一箩筐
Evening, gents What a lovely night for a botched robbery.
这礼拜第三起 一定是趁收假前捞一笔
Yeah, third this week Must be end of summer rush.
我派人带了警犬巡逻公园
I got foot patrols going through the park, dogs are on the way.
被害人是保罗·史坦 死亡时间是10点10分
The victim's name is Paul Stine Dousette pronounced him at 10:10.
嫌犯朝后脑勺开了一枪 司机的钱包 钥匙不见了
Suspect fired one shot to the back of the head Driver's wallet and car keys are missing.
你怎么知道被害人的名字?
How'd you know his name?
李洛指认他 计程车行来的
Leroy, there, came down from Yellow Cab to ID him.
这社区很注重治安 我已经叫拖车过来了
Neighborhood's pretty high end for this kind of thing, so I already set up transpo for the cab.
验尸官来了 有任何目击者吗?
Coroner's here Any witnesses?
小孩从那扇窗看见嫌犯
Kids who called it in saw the suspect from that window.
他们有听见枪声吗? 没有
Did they hear a shot? No.
他们以为嫌犯喝醉 跑到前座去殴打驾驶
They first saw him in the front seat, thought he was a drunk fighting with the driver.
大的那个孩子跑到楼下看清楚
Oldest kid ran downstairs to get a better look from the dining room
她形容嫌犯为男性白人 戴眼镜 平头 健壮结实 穿深色夹克
described him as a white male, glasses, crew cut, stocky, and wearing a dark jacket.
等等 不是说嫌犯是黑人吗? 那是无线电传送的报告
Wait, I thought someone said he was black That's the description that went out to radio cars.
我们已经更正了 那好
We already corrected it Oh, well, that's good.
你们还需要帮忙吗? 不了 走吧
You guys need anything else? No Get out of here.
谢啦 生日快乐
Thanks Happy Birthday.
等下 今天你生日?
Wait, it's your birthday? Yep.
是啊 棒极了 生日快乐!
Yep. That's great Happy birthday Thanks.
多谢了 尸体还是现场? 今天你生日 尸体交给我
Body or scene? It's your birthday, I'll take the body.
大卫 他把车里擦得很干净 这里有些血迹
Dave, looks like he wiped the cab down pretty good We got some blood over here Prints?
指纹呢? 可能有 回局里再采指纹
Could very well be We'll dust it at the Hall.
奇怪的是 还找到手套
The odd thing is, we also got gloves.
嫌犯的吗? 手套上有血迹
Suspect's? There's blood on them.
彼得 好了吗? 我能进去吗?
Hey, Pete? Yeah, Dave You through over there, can I get in there?
谁动了他? 史都华
Yeah, I'm all set Who rolled him? Stewarts.
我找到一枚九毫米弹壳
I got a single 9mm casing.
是啊 鲁格手枪
Yeah, Luger.
围观者没有任何线索
Nothing from the crowd.
假设我是黑人男性嫌犯
Okay I'm your shooter, Negro male adult
其实是健壮结实的平头白人
who also happens to be a stocky, crew cut Caucasian.
我叫了车子 给他这个住址
I flag a cab I give him this address.
我有给他住址吗? 车资记录呢?
Did I give him this address? Who's got the fare book?
在这里
Right here.
华盛顿和枫树街口 东边的那条街口
Washington and Maple That's one block east.
光线和这边差不多 假设我看见有人正在遛狗
Lighting's the same over here, so maybe I see someone walking their dog.
你不希望有任何目击者 所以叫他多开一条街再停车
You don't want any witnesses so you tell him to go down a block He pulls over.
我很聪明 等他排到停车挡
I wait for him to put it in park because I'm smart
以免下手的时候他踩油门
and I don't want him hitting the accelerator when I shoot him May I?
停车 排档 砰!
He stops, puts it in park, boom.
我从右边开枪 他倒向右边?
I shoot him on the right side, he slumps right?
也许你边开枪边抓他的衣领
Maybe you've got your hand on his collar when you shoot.
不管怎样 我在前座 留下了大量血迹
All right So, either way, I just dumped a quart of blood in the front seat.
你为什么要到前座? 为了拿钱
So, why do you get in the front seat? For the money.
他挂了 你只要伸手拿钱包就行
But he's dead You could just reach over the seat, pull out his wallet.
这样根本不用担心沾到血迹
You don't have to go anywhere near the blood.
你为什么要走到前座?
So, why'd he get in the front seat?
因为我是个笨蛋 但你不是笨蛋
I'm an idiot But you're not an idiot.
你等他排档了
You waited for him to put it in park.
谢了 不客气
Right Thank you Yeah, sure.
我能看看吗? 可以
Can I see that? Yeah.
我真笨 为了8块2毛钱杀人
I am an idiot I just killed a man for $8.25.
他是今晚第三名乘客 谁有卡通动物饼干?
It's his third fare of the night Does anyone have any animal crackers?
卡通动物饼干? 在车上
Animal crackers? They're in the car.
我留着等会儿吃
I'm saving those for later.
好吧
Fine.
你是记者吗? 不是 我是旧金山警局的陶希警探
Are you a reporter? No, I'm Inspector Dave Toschi, SFPD.
我能不能分别向您的小孩问话
Sir, I was wondering if I'd be able to talk to your children
最好是单独问话? 他们才刚看到一个人被杀
one at a time and preferably alone? They just saw a man murdered.
我了解
I understand.
他们看起来像喝醉在打架 对啊 他拿了一块破布
It looked like they were drunk and fighting Yeah, and he had a rag.
走到车子旁边擦什么东西
He came around the side of the car and he was wiping stuff.
你有看到他的脸吗?
Did you get a chance to see his face? I did.
我有 算是有吧
Well, sort of.
你记得他长什么样吗?
Did you remember what he looked like?
很普通
Normal Yeah.
是啊 很普通?
"Normal?"
旧金山纪事报 请速交编辑部
速交编辑部
三天后 加州旧金山
我是黄道带 昨晚在华盛顿街
"This is the Zodiac speaking" I am the murderer of the taxi driver
枫树街口杀害计程车司机的凶手
"over by Washington Street and Maple Street last night.
附上被害人一块血衣做为证据
"To prove this, here is a blood stained piece of his shirt.
我也是北湾区命案的凶手
"I am the same man who did in the people in the North Bay Area.
旧金山警方昨晚本来能抓到我
"The S.F Police could have caught him last night
如果他们仔细搜查公园 而不是骑着摩托车到处乱飙
"if they had searched the park properly" instead of holding road races with their motorcicles."
各位 大卫
Gentlemen Dave.
保罗 衬衫在哪里?
Paul Where's the shirt?
在这里 老大
Right there, boss.
这就是小孩说的那块破布 他走到前座撕下衬衫一角
There's your rag the kids talked about So he got in the front seat to tear off a piece of the shirt.
这算正式记录吗? 你认为呢?
Is this on the record? Well, what do you think?
他证实了瓦列霍及那帕的命案
He confirms the Vallejo and Napa killings.
情况还会更糟 罗伯 你不用截稿吗?
Gets worse Robert, do you have a deadline?
情况还会更糟是啥意思?
What does he mean, it gets worse?
念念最后的部分
Read the last part.
小学生是很好的目标
"School children make nice targets.
我要在早上毁掉一辆校车
"I think I shall wipe out a school bus some morning.
先把前轮射穿
"Just shoot out the front tire
然后一个一个把他们干掉
"and then pick off the kiddies as they come bouncing out."
我的天 谁负责管校车? 交通部吗?
Jesus Christ, who's got school buses? Department of Transportation?
校委会 好
School board All right.
我要采集每位员工的指纹
I'm gonna need elimination prints from your staff.
有谁没碰过这封信?
Has anyone here didn't touch this letter?
让他们行动回来 如果你想 他们有带手机
On my way back to my desk They have phones, if you want.
我们要比对血迹及布料
We need to get matches on blood and fabric.
我会连络那帕和瓦列霍警局 将信交给沙加缅度警局进行检验
I'll call Napa and Vallejo, get the letters up to Sherwood in Sacramento.
大卫 真的有在车上采到指纹吗?
Dave, just one thing Is it true they got a print off the cab?
没错 沾到血的部分指纹
Yeah, we got a partial in blood.
这条线索不准刊登 不会吧 干嘛这样?
But that is not for publication Hey, hey, come on.
连我也不准吗?
Hey, it's me.
他说有采到指纹?
Did he say they got a print?
一部分
Partial.
他佩枪的方式跟史帝夫·麦昆一样 是史帝夫·麦昆抄袭陶希警探的
Dude, he wears his gun like Bullitt No, McQueen got that from Toschi.
他觉得黄道带会再寄密码吗? 我觉得他会再寄密码
Does he think that Zodiac's gonna send another code? 'Cause I think Zodiac's gonna send another code.
我的老天 你到底在做什么?
Jesus Harold Christ on rubber crutches, Bobby What are you doing?
你又在干我说过的那档 我不喜欢你干的事
You're doing that thing, the thing we discussed
在我背后偷瞄 喔 穿帮了
the thing that I don't like Starts with an" L."
没错
Oh, looming Yeah.
为了和旧金山警方配合 我们将刊登黄道带的信件 去掉威胁杀伤学童的那一段
In cooperation with SFPD , we will run the Zodiac letter without including the threat on school children.
我们不希望造成市民恐慌
We don't want to start a city wide panic
所以我要请你们保密
so I'm asking all of you to please keep this confidential.
回去继续工作吧 谢谢
Just go about your daily business Thank you.
餐盒中有汽水 红萝卜和花生酱
I packed you your carrots and your soda and peanut butter, okay?
爸 你不用陪我等 我知道
Dad, you don't have to wait with me I know.
等一下 今天我送他上学 好吗?
You know what? You know what? I'm gonna drive him today, okay?
来吧
Come on.
十小时后 加州 沙加缅度 犯罪鉴定与调查局
那是什么?
What's that?
小写的r有类似之处
Similarities in the lowercase" r's."
那个呢? 再说一个字
And that?
就请你到走廊上等 我得集中注意力
It is you waiting in the hall if you speak again I have to concentrate.
抱歉 抱歉也是字
Sorry" Sorry" counts as speaking.
小写的r有类似之处
There are similarities in the lowercase" r's."
我们得发布校车恐吓的消息
We have to release the bus threat.
一发布我们就完了 早就完了
It'll screw us We're already screwed.
我们只是把计程车命案
We just went from" Routine Cabbie Shooting"
改为校园大屠杀
to" Mass Murderer Targets Kids."
黄道带来到了旧金山
The Zodiac Killer has come to San Francisco.
旧金山警方今晚发布声明
Confirmation tonight, from the San Francisco Police Department
他最后寄去的一封信中
that in his latest haunting letter
坦承谋杀计程车司机保罗·史坦
which takes credit for the murder of cab driver Paul Stine
黄道带并扬言威胁说 他将锁定校车
the Zodiac has threatened to," Wipe out a school bus
把上面的学童一一的杀死
"and pick off the kiddies as they come bouncing out."
如果您有关于黄道带的线索
If you think you might know who the Zodiac is
请拨打旧金山警局的报案专线
you can call the San Francisco Police Department's newest tip line.
有潜在同性恋倾向
十二小时后 加州 旧金山
我们需要警察出动
四点钟开记者会 应该给些消息
Press conference is at 4:00 We got to give them something.
我们和教委会配合 应该很快就会有线索
We're coordinating with the school board, and we expect a break in the case very soon.
有什么线索? 接都接不完的电话
What do we really got? We're swamped.
专线打不进来他们就透过总机
When they can't get anyone on the tip line they call the switchboard and keep getting put through.
有具体的嫌犯吗? 每小时90名 目前累积到500名
You got any hard suspects? About 90 an hour I'm up to around 500.
不能缩小范围吗? 我也想 如果我能出去查案
Well, can't you narrow it down? I would love to, if I could get out of this...
重案组 请稍候
Homicide, please hold Yeah, hold, please.
对啦 等一下 我们得告诉民众警方动用全力
We're gonna need to tell them we got the entire force on this.
你能给我多少人力? 目前就你和比尔 周一又要上课
How many men can you give me? Well, right now, it's you and Bill and Monday's a school day.
我知道 我有三个女儿
Yeah, I know, Chief I have three daughters of my own.
我知道 阿姆斯壮呢? 他正在和瓦列霍警局通话
Yeah, I know Where's Armstrong? He's on the phone with Vallejo.
我们需要你们的资料
We're playing catch up, Jack.
我想见见生还者 麦克·梅休
I'd like to set up a meeting with your survivor, Michael Mageau.
没办法 他走人了
I can't He skipped town.
唯一看见凶手真面目的人失踪了?
The only guy who's seen Zodiac without a mask is missing?
在医院我们有整天让他指认
When he was still in the hospital we could show him lineups all day long.
但是他一出院就落跑了 是吗 为什么?
As soon as he got out, he split Really? Why?
我猜他不想被拖下水
I don't think he wanted to have anything to do with this.
你能寄来手上有的资料吗?
Can you send us everything that you have?
这应该是双方面的吧
Well, the road goes both ways.
我们需要计程车上采到的指纹
Now, we need that print you lifted from the cab
还有嫌犯那封信的笔迹
and we should have been in on the handwriting.
抱歉 事情发生得太快
I apologize Things have been moving fast.
那帕那里该跟谁联络配合?
Who should I talk to in Napa so we can coordinate?
找肯恩·纳尔罗
Talk to Ken Narlow.
我们应该拿到嫌犯的笔迹
We really should have been in on the handwriting.
抱歉 事情发生得太快
I apologize Things have been moving fast.
我们需要犯罪现场的照片 办不到
Listen, we're gonna need your scene photos Can't help you.
肯恩 我不想跟你争管辖权
Ken, I don't want to get into a jurisdictional thing here.
不是啦 是我们没有犯罪现场
No, no, no, no, no We didn't have a crime scene.
巡警几乎把现场彻底破坏了
The ranger that found the kids literally swept everything into a picnic blanket.
我们只采集到一些鞋印 什么?
All we have are the Wing Walker prints The what?
往返犯罪现场十号半男用长靴
Boot prints to and from the crime scene were made by size 10 and a half Wing Walkers
军用品专卖店才买得到的军靴
military style boots sold only at military PXs
特别设计用来行走在机翼
designed to walk on the wings of planes.
你得有军用识别证才能购买
And you can't buy at a PX without a military ID
所以嫌犯有可能是职业军人
so our suspect could be military.
你们有因此缩小范围吗? 有
Did you guys narrow your list off of this?
瓦列霍警方呢?
Yeah Did Vallejo?
不知道 那不是我的辖区
I don't know I don't work in Vallejo I work here.
我需要那些鞋印的照片 没问题 你先把那封信寄过来
Great I'm gonna need photos of those boot prints Sure, if you send me the handwriting.
鉴识组不是寄了备份吗?
I thought Questioned Documents already did.
没 瓦列霍警局有收到 我们没有
Nope Vallejo's got them, not us.
我会请他们 算了 我电传给你
All right I'll have Questioned Documents... Forget it I'll telefax it to you.
我们没有电传机
We don't have telefax yet.
好 我立刻邮寄过去 我们也会寄出资料
Okay, I'll put it in the mail We'll mail ours, too.
打给穆拉斯 或许他能给你油印的
And call Mulanax in Vallejo Maybe he can get you a mimeo Right.
何不直接要石膏模的照片?
Why don't you just get a photo off the original plaster cast?
还要等 因为他们没有电传机
We'd have to wait, because they don't have a fax.
我们也没有
We don't have a fax, either.
我只希望彼此能互相配合 你打给索拉诺的警长办公室了吗?
Look, I'm just trying to get us coordinated Have you called Solano Sheriff's Office?
为什么要打到索拉诺?
Why would I call Solano?
因为去年圣诞节的命案 隶属索拉诺辖区
Because the two kids that got killed last Christmas were Solano's.
我以为他们在瓦列霍的辖区 不对 犯罪现场在边界
I thought they were Vallejo No, they were over the county line
- 你必须和双方配合 - 好吧
- So you're gonna need to coordinate with them, too. - Okay.
比尔 我能和你说句话吗?
Bill Can I have a word with you?
你在哪里看到这家伙?
Where did you see this guy?
我们奉命去那里找一名男性黑人
We got the call to circle the scene and look for a Negro male adult.
当时他在哪里?
Where was he?
杰克森街 往东差不多半条街
On Jackson Heading east About the middle of the block.
枪击案发生后三分钟左右 差不多
And this is three minutes after the shooting? Give or take Yeah.
你们往东还是往西? 我们往西
And you were heading east or west? We were going west.
你们当时在西向杰克森街
All right, so you're on Jackson going west.
计程车在西南方一条街口外
So the cab was one block catty corner southwest?
是的 你有慢下来吗? 我们当然有慢下来
Correct Did you slow down? Of course we slowed down All right.
勤务中心说嫌犯是男性黑人
Listen, Dispatch said it was a Negro male.
后来更正了
That was corrected.
我们发现他时还没更正
No, but at the time they hadn't changed it.
而且他是白人 看来不赶时间 步伐又很笨重
This guy was white Right, not in a hurry Kind of lumbering along like...
步伐笨重? 什么意思?
Lumbering? What do you mean," lumbering"?
拖着脚走路 健壮结实 平头吗?
Shuffling Stocky? Had a crew cut?
对 没有错
Yeah, that's all correct.
听着 当时很暗
Listen, it was dark.
他又穿着深色夹克 根本无法
The guy was wearing a dark jacket There's no way...
他可能全身沾满了血
He would have been covered in blood.
你有拦下他?
Did you stop him?
有没有问他话?
Did you talk to him?
有? 没有? 没有
Yes? No? No.
去找人画张素描
You need to get with a sketch artist.
立刻把新的嫌犯画像发布出去
We have to put out a new composite right away.
旧金山目前累计五名被害人
Five persons have been murdered in the San Francisco area
而每起案件
and in each case the killer...
我要在早上向一辆校车下手
"I shall wipe out a school bus some morning..."
旧金山警方
San Francisco police...
本周日滚石乐团举行演唱会
to see the Stones in concert this Sunday.
旧金山纪事报 收到
The new letters from the Zodiac Killer were sent to
来自黄道带的最新信件
the City room of the San Francisco Chronicle One of the letters was...
别在我背后偷瞄
Looming No looming.
你有想过"水理论" ? 什么?
Have you considered the water theory? What?
犯罪现场不是在水边 就是死者姓名与水有关
Geographically, every attack takes place near a body of water
这就是你的水理论 贝瑞莎湖 蓝石泉
or a water based name This is your water theory? Lake Berryessa Blue Rock Springs.
赫曼湖" 滑" 盛顿和樱桃街口?
Lake Herman Wash ington and Cherry?
你觉得呢? 不合理
You think? No.
我在读这本 谋杀案调查
I'm reading this book, Homicide Investigation by Lemoyne Snyder...
李·蒙奈·史奈德著 是李·摩
"Leymone." ...and he says you look for patterns
他说要从犯案模式着手调查
so I'm looking for patterns No.
不 这不是件普通的刑事案件
You can't think of this case in normal police terms.
为什么不是? 有四个案发现场
Why not? You got four crime scenes.
索拉诺 瓦列霍 贝瑞莎和这里
Solano, Vallejo, Berryessa, and here.
前三个案发地点以及信件 都没有采到有效的指纹
Not a single usable print at the first three or in any of the letters?
这个犯罪天才为什么会突然跑来 留下一枚沾血指纹?
How does our master criminal come to the city and leave a bloody latent?
假设手套是嫌犯的
I mean, assuming the gloves are his
难道他杀了司机后又脱下来?
he shoots the cabbie and then takes them off?
所以那不是他的指纹?
So it's not his print?
或许是或许不是 这不是重点
Maybe, maybe not You're missing the point.
重点是第一起谋杀案 大卫·法瑞戴和贝蒂·珍森 双双身亡
The point is the first attack... David Faraday and Betty Jensen They both die.
他之后就只杀害女性
From there on out, he only manages to kill the girls.
他并不是没尽力 并不是
Not for lack of trying Not for lack of trying.
梅休存活 费伦死亡 哈特奈尔生还 薛伯没有
Mageau lives, Ferrin dies Hartnell lives, Shepard dies.
他对女人特别投入 忘了要杀死男人
He gets so caught up with the women he forgets to finish off the men.
加上他们是在野外约会的情侣
Plus, they're all couples and all on lover's lanes.
保罗·史坦就不是 没错
Paul Stine is not Exactly.
单身男性司机不符合这些条件
Single, male cab driver on Washington and Cherry doesn't fit.
不符合
Doesn't fit.
那么黄道带为什么要杀他?
So, why does Zodiac kill him?
他在改变犯案模式
He's breaking the pattern.
- 喂? - 有人自称是黄道带 半小时前打给奥克兰警局
- Yeah? - Someone claiming to be Zodiac called Oakland PD a half hour ago.
他说三小时后 会叩应吉姆·顿巴的现场谈话节目
He says he's gonna call in on Jim Dunbar's morning show in three hours.
在电视上吗? 他要梅尔文·贝利当他的律师
On television? He wants Melvin Belli on to counsel him.
好 快把梅尔文叫醒
All right All right Let's go wake up Melvin.
卡通动物饼干?
Animal crackers?
在置物箱
Glove box.
这些是防弹车窗吗?
Are these windows bulletproof?
对 梅尔文 你不必躺在下面
Yes, Melvin You don't have to lie down back there.
这家伙是枪神 随时都能让我一枪毙命
This man is a marksman, could snuff me out at a moment's notice.
你确定你行吗?
Are you sure you're up for this?
不用担心我 警探 灯光一亮我就会没事了
Don't you worry about me, Inspector I'll be fine when the lights are on.
这个男人向我求救
This man has asked for my help.
你担心的那个 随时可能射杀你的男人
The man you're worrying about snuffing you out?
这些是什么 饼干?
What are these, cookies?
老天爷 你有清过车子吗?
Dear Lord, do you ever clean this car?
可恶 其它新闻台得到消息了
Shit KGO must have tipped other stations.
让他说话 说服他跟你见面
Get him talking Convince him to meet you somewhere.
如果你有机会 请他到中国城圣玛丽教堂碰面
If you see an opportunity, we want you to suggest Old St Mary's Church in Chinatown.
你们会追踪电话?
You'll be tracing the call?
你要让他在线上十五分钟以上
Pacific Telephone says you need to keep him on the line for 15 minutes.
应该可以 对吧 吉姆?
We can do that, can't we, Jim?
十五秒 清空摄影棚
Fifteen seconds Clear the set.
拿去吧 你这个醉鬼
Here you go, you drunken reprobate.
我们要中断节目插播一则新闻
We interrupt our regular program to bring you this news bulletin.
欢迎收看本集特别节目 现场邀请黄道带
Welcome to this special edition of our show in which we are joined by attorney Melvin Belli
亲自指定的律师 梅尔文·贝利律师
who the Zodiac Killer personally requested to appear.
快吃完 然后放到水槽
Finish up, buddy, and put it in the sink.
早安 梅尔文 早安 吉姆
Good morning, Melvin Good morning, Jim.
电话线已开放 贝利也在现场
So, the phone lines are open Mr. Belli is here.
我很乐意帮忙 没错 你是来帮忙
Here to help, Jim Yes Here to help.
请民众不要拨打进来占线 好让黄道带本人可以和我们连线
And we ask the public not to call in, so that the Zodiac himself can reach us.
我看了你演出 星际迷航记 演得很棒
I saw your Star Trek, by the way It was excellent.
可惜停播了 工作人员都很好
A shame about the show Good people.
我常常考虑成为全职演员
You know, I've often thought of becoming an actor full time.
你的角色叫什么? 戈耳冈
What was your character's name?
戈耳冈 没错
Gorgon Gorgon That's right.
快录音 开始录音 我们接到电话 准备上现场
Roll the tape Get the tape Jim, we have a call We're going live.
喂?
Hello?
你好 这是梅尔文·贝利
Hello? This is Melvin Belli.
请问你是谁?
Who am I speaking with?
我是黄道带
This is the Zodiac speaking.
你有没有别的名字? 比较没这么恐怖的
Is there something I can call you that's a little less ominous?
山姆
Sam Sam.
我们可以在什么地方见面谈一谈吗 山姆?
Is there somewhere we can meet, Sam, and talk about this?
在费蒙特宾馆楼顶见我
Meet me on top of the Fairmont Hotel.
自己来否则我会跳楼自杀...
Without anyone else or I'll jump...
马上派人去费蒙特宾馆
Have a unit go to the Fairmont Hotel.
山姆 是的
Sam Yes?
山姆 你认为你需要医疗协助吗?
Do you think you need medical care?
我是生了病 但不是疯子
Medical, not mental.
你的健康出了问题?
Do you have health problems?
我病了 我头很痛
I'm sick I have headaches.
头痛?
Headaches?
我也有头痛 但我的颈椎治疗师把我治好了
I have headaches, too, but a chiropractor stopped them a week ago.
我认为我能帮助你 山姆
I think I can help you, Sam.
山姆?
Sam?
他知道电话会被追踪
He knows they're tracing his calls.
山姆 我们要让你知道 我们没有追踪你的电话
Sam, we'd like you to know that we are not tracing these calls.
追踪过程冗长而且复杂 短时间的通话也无法追踪
It's a long, difficult process and ineffective with these short calls.
山姆?
Sam?
我们没有追踪电话 我保证
We're not tracing these calls You have my word.
好吧
Okay.
山姆 你得告诉我你的问题
Sam, you need to tell me what your problem is.
我不想进毒气室 我有头痛 杀了人就不会头痛
I don't want to go to the gas chamber I have headaches I kill, I don't get them.
他脑袋真他妈坏了！
That is fucked up!
你想活 对吧? 我就是你的救星
You want to live, don't you? Well, this is your passport.
你头痛有多久了?
How long have you been having these headaches?
从我杀了那小子开始
Since I killed a kid.
你有头晕现象没? 有
Do you have blackouts? Yes.
有没有痉挛? 不 我只是头痛
Do you have fits? No I just have headaches.
两三个星期前贝利先生来我台做客时
Did you attempt to call one other time
你有没有给他打过电话?
when F Lee Bailey was with us two or three weeks ago?
打过
Yes.
为什么你想和贝利先生谈话呢?
And why did you want to talk to Mr. Bailey?
你为什么想要和我谈话呢 山姆?
Why do you wanna tal k to me, Sam?
我不想被伤害 他为什么打电话?
I don't want to be hurt Why is he calling?
我不想进毒气室 等一下 宝贝
Hey, just a second, buddy I don't wanna go to the gas chamber.
你跟我说话就不会受伤
You won't get hurt if you talk to me.
你也不会进毒气室
And you're not going to the gas chamber.
我想他们不至于判你死刑
I wouldn't think they would ask for capital punishment.
我们可以问问检察官 你要我这么做吗 山姆?
We should ask the District Attorney Do you want me to do that, Sam?
你要我问检察官吗?
Do you want me to talk to the District Attorney?
那是什么 山姆?
What was that, Sam?
我没有说话
I did not say anything.
我们听到一声尖叫
We heard a scream.
那是我的头痛
That was my headache.
听起来你的疼痛很剧烈
You sound like you're in a great deal of pain.
我头很痛 我病的很严重
My head aches I'm so sick.
我要杀光他们
I'm gonna kill them.
好 我要杀死那些孩子
Oh, okay I'm gonna kill those kids!
这可真棒
Fantastic.
山姆?
Sam?
让我们碰面 就我们两个 好吧
Let's meet and talk Just us Okay.
在中国城的圣玛丽教堂如何?
How about Old St Mary's Church in Chinatown?
不 十点半在戴利市 圣文森慈善商店门口
No, In front of the Daly City St Vincent de Paul at 10:30.
到时候见
I'll see you there.
好好保重 山姆
Take care of yourself, Sam.
圣文森慈善商店
天啊 你们这群人可真了解 私下密会的意思
My, my, my You fellows certainly know how to put on a secret meeting.
贝利 这里
You know, the problem is
我不想进毒气室 我有头痛 我杀了人就不会头痛
I don't want to go to the gas chamber I have headaches I kill, I don't get them.
不 那不是他
No, it's not him.
这声音偏高 也比较年轻
It's the voice The voice is too high It's too young.
多谢你来一趟 布莱恩
All right Thanks for coming down, Bryan.
没关系 我自己来
Do you have blackouts? That's okay I got it.
他们停止追踪了 这位没来赴约的神经病
They pulled off the trace Our Daly City no show called from a mental institution.
奥克兰警局接线生很确定 跟他说话的男人声音更低沉
Oakland PD's operator is sure the man she talked to had a deeper voice.
也更冷静 搞不好真的是这家伙
Calmer Might have actually been him.
我要改变收藏奴隶的方法
"So I shall change my way of collecting slaves.
两周半后 加州 旧金山
我不会再通知任何人我要犯案
"I shall no longer announce to anyone when I commit my murders.
命案看起来会像一般抢劫 殴斗
"They shall look like routine robberies, killings of anger
假造的意外 等等
"and a few fake accidents, et cetera.
警方永远逮不到我 因为我远比那些笨蛋聪明
"The police shall never catch me" because I have been too clever for them.
警方所公布的嫌犯素描 是我犯案时的模样
"I look like the description passed out only when I do my thing.
其余时间我则是完全不同面貌
"The rest of the time I look entirely different.
我不会告诉你们我杀人时的伪装
"I shall not tell you what my disguise consists of when I kill.
我也没有像警方说的那样
"As of yet I have left no fingerprints behind me
留下任何指纹
"contrary to what the police say.
我都戴透明指尖套
"I wear transparent fingertips.
你们只会采集到我指尖 涂上的两层模型黏胶
"All it is is two coats of airplane cement coated on my fingertips.
恶整那两个巡警很好玩 猪头 当时我人就在公园
"I enjoy needling the blue pigs Hey, blue pig, I was in the park.
你们多叫了几辆消防车 掩盖巡逻警车的声音
"You were using fire trucks to mask the sound of your cruising prowl cars.
猪头 被人戳破这些糗事 你们一定超不爽吧?
"Hey, pig, doesn't it rile you up" to have your nose rubbed in your booboos?
警方要是真以为 我会向校车下手
"If you cops think I am going to take on a bus the way I stated I was
你们真的是脑袋坏了
"you deserve to have holes in your heads."
你最好看看这玩意儿
And you need to look at this.
一袋硝酸氨肥料
"Take one bag of ammonium nitrate fertilizer
一加仑沙拉油 上面再洒上几袋砂砾
"one gallon of stove oil," and dump a few bags of gravel on top..."
他说的是炸弹
Okay It's a bomb.
我们得打给军方
Okay We gotta call the Army and see if this
证实这种土制炸药的可行性
science experiment could actually work.
又有一组密码
Another cipher.
这是什么时候来的? 今天早上
When did these arrive? They arrived this morning.
你打算刊登吗? 罗伯
Are you planning to publish? Robert.
我们应该去喝一杯
We should have a drink.
谢谢
Thank you.
谈谈你自己 结婚了吗?
So, tell me about yourself.
离婚了 两个小孩
You married? Divorced Two kids.
都做些什么休闲活动?
What do you do for fun?
我很喜欢阅读
I love to read.
我喜欢看书 那不是一样吗?
I enjoy books Those are the same things.
干嘛翻我的垃圾?
Why you been going through my trash?
待会儿再说好了
I'll come back to that.
你怎么知道他还会再寄密码? 我猜的
How did you know he was gonna send another code? I just guessed.
只是猜的 第一组似乎过于简单
Just guessed The first one seemed too easy.
好吧 再也不能视而不见了
All right, this can no longer be ignored.
告诉我 你到底喝什么东东? 蓝色刮胡水调酒
What is that you're drinking? It's an Aqua Velva.
如果你试了 就不会开我的玩笑了
You wouldn't make fun of it if you tried it.
是谁破解了密码?
But who actually cracked the code?
一对喜欢解谜的夫妻 这让我们知道黄道带是什么人?
A married couple who like puzzles So what's that tell us about the Zodiac?
他不是密码专家 没错 这就像小时候上童军课
He's no expert Right It's just a simple substitution code
会用的替代编码法
like the one that we used to do as boy scouts.
A是1 B是2 不是每个人都上过童军课
"A" is one," B" is two We weren't all boy scouts, Robert.
这并不难 只要先找到关键字
Well, it's not that hard You just got to know where to start.
第一组密码  你竟然把密码带在身上
In the first cipher... You actually carry that around with you?
怎样? 没怎样
Why? No reason.
英文最常用到哪两个子音组合?
What's the most common double consonant in the English language?
子音? 双L
Consonant?
双L
The double" L." Double" L."
哪个字他至少会用上一次?
And what's the one word that we know that he'll use in here, at least once?
杀 对 杀KILL
"Kill." Right," kill."
哈顿夫妻先找相同的两个符号 找到这里 这里 还有这里
So the Hardens start looking for double symbols, which they find here, here, and here.
前面都有一样的两个符号
Each with the same two symbols preceding them.
现在他们找到好几个两个一样符号的 四个字母的字
So now they've got a repeating four letter word ending with two symbols that they assume stand for" L."
他们认为这个字串是KILL
And since they think the whole word is" kill" then...
有了K和I 这就是个关键字
Then you got your" K" you got your" I" and you're on your way.
他们怎么用这两个符号 解开整个谜?
But how do you go from" A" is one and" B" is two to figuring out this whole code?
就像我一样 去图书馆查
Well, same way I did You go to the library.
在这本书里
In this book
作者在序中提供简单的替代字
the author presents a very simple substitution code in the preface.
他提供的26个替代字中 就有8个在这张密码里找得到
Eight of the 26 symbols that he suggests are found in this cipher.
但这些都不是字母 看起来是中世纪符号
Yeah, but there are non letter symbols because there's all these medieval ones.
我也这么觉得
I thought they looked medieval, too.
后来我意外发现中世纪密码 猜猜看它叫什么?
But then I found a code written in the Middle Ages Guess what it's called?
黄道带字母
The Zodiac Alphabet.
天呐
Jesus.
你想得到什么好处? 什么?
What do you want out of this?
你有什么企图? 除了你以外别人都能捞到好处
What? What's your angle? This is good business for everyone but you.
你指的好处是什么?
How do you mean" business"?
上床睡觉吧
Hey Come to bed.
待会儿再睡 我得打通电话
I'll be up in a minute I need to make a phone call.
喂? 比尔?
Hello? Bill?
加州并没有太多的地下室
There's not many basements in California.
以后会派上用场的地下室
"Basement for future use."
没错
That's right.
我会打给瓦列霍和那帕市 请城市规划局调查 去睡吧
I'll have Vallejo and Napa check with their city planners Get some sleep Yeah, sure.
一个半月后 加州 旧金山
亲爱的梅尔文 我是黄道带
"Dear Melvin, this is the Zodiac speaking.
希望你有个愉快的圣诞节
"I wish you a happy Christmas.
我只想请你帮忙 请你帮助我
"The one thing I ask of you is this Please help me.
我无法向其他人求助 因为我心里的声音不肯
"I cannot reach out for help because this thing in me won't let me."
谢了
Thank you.
我发现我就快要失去控制
"I am finding it extremely difficult to hold it in check
我担心我一旦失去控制 就会有第九个
"and I am afraid I will lose control again
或第十个受害者出现
"and take my ninth and possibly tenth victim."
梅尔文 他在向你求救
Melvin, he's reaching out to you.
一点也没错 警探 这封信直接寄到我家
Absolutely Inspectors, he sent this letter directly to my residence.
与其说是声明不如说是求救信
It is a cry for help, intended as a private communiqué
所以你才通知 旧金山纪事报
Which is why you contacted the Chronicle.
民众有权利知道事实 来一杯?
The people have a right to know Toddy?
你几时收到信? 上礼拜中旬
When did the letter arrive? In the middle of last week.
我旅游参观去了
I was away on safari.
先生们你们圣诞节要怎么过?
What did you gentlemen do for Christmas?
就像现在这样 你一定要去非洲看看
You're looking at it You must see Africa.
文明的起源 魅力人民 漂亮 野性
Cradle of civilization Fascinating people Beautiful Savage.
拜托让我们回到杀手上来 哦 当然
Back to the killer who wrote to you Yes Of course.
我相信他写这封信是因为
It is my belief that he only penned this letter
他打到电视台或我家都找不到我
because he couldn't get through to me on the Dunbar show or here.
他有试着打电话到你家? 好几次 我都不在
He tried to contact you here? Several times.
他和女管家说过话
I was out, but he spoke with my housekeeper.
没留下号码
Didn't leave a number.
他一向都很狡猾 介意我跟你管家谈谈吗?
He's kind of crafty like that Do you mind if I speak to her?
不介意 但是这封信比较重要
Not at all But the real story is the letter.
我马上回来 好
I'll be back Yeah.
她在这里 陶希警探
She's right this way.
我相信这封信  是通往他灵魂的窗口
Inspector Toschi, it is my belief this is a window into this man's soul.
他内心有杀戮的冲动
Killing is his compulsion.
他想忽视却无法抵抗 这是他的本性
Even though he tries to ignore it, it drives him It's in his blood.
也许他只是想出风头
Could be Or maybe he just likes the attention.
一个半月后 132号公路 加州 莫德斯托附近
1970年3月22日
我不是故意吓你 你的车子右轮胎松了
I didn't mean to scare you, but your right rear wheel is loose.
真的吗? 你要的话 我可以帮你锁紧
Really? If you like, I could tighten the lugs up for you.
你不介意的话 还是小心一点比较好
If you don't mind Well, you can't be too careful.
搞定了 谢谢
All done Thank you.
不客气 祝你愉快
No problem Have a good night.
没事
It's okay.
你没事吗?
Are you okay?
没事 我们没事
Yeah Yeah, we're fine.
一定比我想像的更严重 我可以载你到加油站修车
Must have been worse than I thought I can give you a lift to a service station.
好啊
Okay.
没关系 来吧
It's okay Come on.
我不知道你有小宝宝
I didn't know you had a baby.
可以吗?
Oh, is that okay?
人越多越好
The more the merrier.
你不该抽烟 这是坏习惯
You shouldn't smoke It's a bad habit.
我们错过了一间加油站 他们打烊了
I think we just passed a filling station It was closed.
你常在晚上四处帮助别人吗?
Do you always go around helping people in the night?
等我搞定 他们就不太需要帮忙
When I'm done with them, they don't need much help.
没事的
It's okay.
在我杀你之前
Before I kill you
我得先把你的小宝宝丢出去
I'm gonna throw your baby out the window.
不要 救命 不要!
No! Help! Please! No!
她人在路边 她把我拦了下来
She was on the side of the road She flagged me down.
发生什么事? 她说她跳车
What happened to her? She said she jumped from a car.
我看到她的时候她就是这样
I found her like this.
怎么了? 求求你 他说
What is it? Please, he said...
一切都没事了 他想要杀我
It'll be okay Tried to kill me.
我的小宝宝! 你的小宝宝呢? 我停车的时候没看到
My baby! Where's her baby? She didn't have one when I stopped.
你的小宝宝呢?
Where's your baby?
老天爷
Jesus.
你藏起来了? 以防他再回来
You hid it? In case he came back.
莫德斯托蜜蜂报
女人声称被黄道带绑架
我是黄道带
"This is the Zodiac speaking.
对了 上个密码破解了吗?
"By the way, have you cracked the last cipher I sent you?
我有点好奇我的人头现在值多少
"I'm mildly curious as to how much money you have on my head now.
希望你没以为我用炸弹
"I hope you do not think I was the one who wiped out that blue meanie
黄道带寄信表示杀了十人
在警局炸死那个白痴巡警
"with a bomb at the cop station
虽然我说过要炸死那些学童
"even though I talked about killing children with one."
我是黄道带
"This is the Zodiac speaking.
我很想在街上看到大家 别上黄道带胸章
"I'd like to see some nice Zodiac buttons wandering around town.
别人都做了胸章
"Everyone else has these buttons
像是和平 黑色力量 律师吃屎之类的胸章
"like peace, black power, and Melvin eats blubber, et cetera.
我会很高兴看到每个人 都别上一枚我的胸章
"It would cheer me up considerably" if I saw a lot of people wearing my button.
别把标语写得太贱"" 我是黄道带
"Please no nasty ones."" This is the Zodiac speaking.
我用38口径旧金山警用手枪 射杀一名驾驶
"I shot a man sitting in a parked car with a .38" Zodiac 12, SFPD zero."
地图加密码提供炸弹的地点
"The map coupled with this code will tell you where the bomb is set.
引爆时间是下一个秋天
"You have until next fall to dig it up."
我是黄道带
"This is the Zodiac speaking.
你们不别黄道带胸章让我很不爽
"I'm rather unhappy because you people" will not wear some nice Zodiac buttons.
我列出一张名单 从那女人和她小孩开始
"So, I now have a little list, starting with the woman and her baby" that I gave a rather interesting ride
四周后 加州 旧金山
几个月前 在我烧毁她车子以前
"for a couple of hours one evening, a few months back
我们一同兜风了几个小时
"that ended in my burning her car where I found them."
我们真的不再刊登这些信件?
We're really not gonna run any more of his letters?
新策略 警方要我们暂时不理他 看他会有什么反应
The new policy Our brothers in blue want us to hold back and see how he reacts.
三个月来四封信
Four letters in three months
这是第一封提到凯萨琳琼斯的 超奇怪的
and this is the first mention of Kathleen Johns That's very weird.
因为他都在讲屁话
That's because he's full of shit.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
你不知道吗?
You don't know?
欢迎 放下你身上的东西 走到第五排左转
Welcome Please put your stuff down You're going down five rows and left.
找三月份的 莫德斯托蜜蜂报
Looking for the Modesto Bee from March.
我会站着试着不吐出来
I'm going to stand here and attempt not to vomit.
左转
Left Left.
我要找什么? 凯萨琳·琼斯
What am I looking for? Kathleen Johns.
也许你要找旧的 纪事报 算了 我自己来找
Also probably you wanna pull the Chron from... You know, never mind I'll see to that.
再读这封信 关于凯萨琳
Okay, look at this letter again The part about Kathleen Johns.
告诉我他说的事实
Tell me what facts he gives.
女人与小孩被他绑架 没错
A woman and her baby abducted Fact.
车子着火 好 现在
The car on fire Okay, now
再看 蜜蜂报 的报导
look at the article from the Bee.
女人声称被黄道带绑架
看到了吗?
Seen it yet?
信上写的都是发生过的事 他以前也玩过这把戏
Everything in the letter already appeared in the article And he's done it before.
警员赖·理查在车上惨遭射杀
Officer Richard Radetich, shot sitting in his car.
黄道带也说他杀了一名驾驶员
Zodiac claimed that he shot someone in their car.
几天后 这则新闻出来 嫌犯早就被逮捕
Couple days after this article came out The police already had somebody in custody.
黄道带根本没犯案 他抢了这些人的功劳
Zodiac didn't do it, but took credit for it anyway
因为他想当媒体宠儿
because he's in it for the press.
他甚至盗用别人的符号 什么?
He even stole his symbol What? Yeah Shit.
我给你看样东西 别告诉别人
If I show you something, you promise not to tell anyone?
我能告诉谁? 对哦 一点也没错
Who would I tell? Okay Totally solid point Okay.
我们收到黄道带的信之前
That's the only place that word and that symbol
符号与名字只同时出现在这里
ever appeared together before the letters.
这家伙盗用手表上的商标 他杀了十三人
The guy stole his logo off a watch How can somebody who's killed 13 people do...
他自称杀了十三人 谁能证明?
He claims he's killed 13 people, but which ones can we actually confirm?
瓦列霍三人 贝瑞莎一人 以及计程车司机 就这样
There's three in Vallejo, one in Berryessa, the cabbie That's it.
小葛 你好像很失望
Bobby, you almost look disappointed.
局长撤走调查此案的人员
Chief's pulling everybody off buses.
一切恢复正常 他一定会再出声
Business as usual Something'll shake loose.
四个月来一声也没吭 起先他不肯住嘴 现在
Not a peep in four months First he won't shut up and now...
也许他被逼得躲起来了
Maybe we drove him underground.
也许他落跑了
Maybe he's gone.
赫特街582号发生案件 有一名男子
311 at 582 Haight, cross at Biltmore There's a male...
比尔 生日快乐 谢了
Happy birthday, Bill Thanks.
1970年10月11日 加州 旧金山 华盛顿街与樱桃街转角
你介意别人老是叫你矮子吗?
Does it ever bother you that people call you Shorty?
你介意别人老是叫你智障吗?
Does it bother you that people call you a retard?
没人这样叫我啊 是啊
Nobody calls me that Right.
我当选后将以州长拥有的权限
As governor, I pledge to use all my influence
把害黛琳费伦的凶手绳之以法
to make sure that Darlene Ferrin's killer is brought to justice.
我相信这起命案有些线索被忽略
I believe some clues were overlooked in the murder of Darlene Ferrin.
我相信这是一起预谋谋杀案 那女人是谁?
I believe her murder was premeditated Who is that?
芙伦丝·道格拉斯 瓦列霍市长 她要出来竞选州长
Florence Douglas, mayor of Vallejo She's running for governor.
我相信警方不是没钱 没时间
I believe that the police department either did not have the money, the time
就是懒得去挖掘真相
or, yes, the inclination...
你竟然敢批评警方 好样的 小芙
Sayonara, police endorsement Good work, Flo.
有人替我取过外号吗?
Does anyone ever call me names, or...
你是说智障吗? 对
You mean like retard? Yeah.
没有
No.
可恶 我靠 他妈的
Shit Fuck Oh, my God Jesus.
告诉我那不是一块沾血衬衫
Tell me that's not a piece of bloody shirt! Fuck! Holy fucking crap!
我知道你们打心里想知道我名字
"I feel it in my bones, you ache to know my name
我就直接告诉你们吧 不过何必扫兴呢? 万圣节快乐
"and so I'll clue you in" But then, why spoil the game? Happy Halloween."
保罗 你在一篇文章中  说他有潜在性同性恋倾向
Paul, you did call him a latent homosexual in at least one of your articles.
大卫 我需要一把枪
Dave I want a gun.
一把枪?
A gun?
专栏作家贺伯·肯恩提到你
You're in Herb Caen.
保罗·艾瑞的深入调查 换来黄道带的一句警告" 你死定了"
"Paul Avery's investigation has won him the accolade" of a message from the Zodiac warning, 'You are doomed.'
结果记者都纷纷别上写着
"As a result, several crime newsmen are wearing lapel buttons reading
"我不是保罗·艾瑞" 的胸章
"'I am not Paul Avery."'
你应该去卖胸章 肯定赚翻天
You should sell these You could do well.
从报社刊登警告信的那天起 我的确收获不少
It's been a windfall, since they published the threat on my life.
线索来自四面八方 有个家伙住在河滨市
I got the leads coming out of the woodwork There's one guy down in Riverside.
今晚我会去找他 一起来吗? 不了 我有个约会
I'm gonna drive down and see him tonight You wanna tag along? No, I have a date.
真的假的? 河滨市这家伙是谁?
Really? Who is this guy?
他想要匿名 我想要声名狼藉
He wishes to remain anonymous I wish to remain infamous.
咱们应该会很合得来
So we're going to get along great.
晚安 我来找梅乐妮
Hi Good evening Hi I'm looking for a Melanie.
自己一个人坐那边的女生 谢谢
Yes It's the young lady sitting by herself Thank you.
你应该是梅乐妮
You must be Melanie.
那你就是罗伯啰! 是的
Which would make you Robert It would.
葛列妮丝说了很多关于你的事
Glynnis told me lots about you.
你在喝葡萄酒 很好 是啊
And you have wine, great I do.
我迟到多久了?
Great How late am I?
几分钟而已 我也是刚到
Just a few minutes, really I just got here myself.
路上塞车 我刚从靶场过来
Traffic's bumper to bumper I was at the gun range.
葛列妮丝说你是个漫画家
Glynnis said you were a cartoonist Oh, yeah.
你去靶场做什么? 看书
Well, what're you doing at a gun range? Reading.
多拿一些 你需要多点餐巾纸
Get some more... You need some more napkins.
你和葛列妮丝是同事?
So, you work with Glynnis.
其实我是替她工作 替她工作?
For her, actually For her?
喔 这样
Oh, well...
我小孩很怕葛列妮丝
My children are terrified of Glynnis.
我也是
Me, too.
你刚才在靶场 我们在调查
So, the gun range?
你知道黄道带? 知道
We're... I'm working on... Do you know the Zodiac?
我和...你知道保罗·艾瑞是谁吗? 有点耳熟
Yeah I'm working with... Do you know who Paul Avery is? Sounds kind of familiar.
他就是遭黄道带恐吓的记者
He's the writer that the Zodiac threatened.
对 我在电视上有看到 其实我跟他是同事
Oh, yeah, I saw that on TV Well, I work near him and he's going down tonight
他今晚要开车到河滨市 找一位匿名密报者
to track an anonymous tipster down in Riverside.
河滨市到底在哪里?
Where is Riverside?
洛杉矶附近
It's near L.A.
我猜保罗不知道路程那么远
Oh, wow I don't think Paul knows that it's that far away.
听起来有些危险
Sounds kind of dangerous.
是啊 怎么说?
Yeah How do you mean?
你不是说对方是个匿名密报者吗?
Well, you said it was an anonymous tip, right?
是啊
Yeah.
可能是个埋伏 搞不好是黄道带
So it could be an ambush I mean, it could be the Zodiac.
你不觉得这么做有点傻吗?
Don't you think it's kind of stupid?
是啊 不过保罗有把枪
Yeah, yeah Well, Paul has a gun.
你知道这里有什么好吃的?
So, do you know what's good here?
我从来没来过这里
I've never been here before.
意大利面?
The pasta, spaghetti?
可以点餐了吗?
Are you ready to order yet?
我要点红酱通心粉 你能帮我改用白酱煮吗?
Yeah, I'll have the penne vodka But could you do it in a cream sauce?
当然可以
Of course.
再给我们几分钟?
Maybe give us another minute?
你有零钱吗?
Do you have any change?
等等 等一下
Oh, wait, no wait, hold on.
没有 我只有一分钱 你要打电话吗?
Nope That's a penny Do you have to make a phone call?
刚刚你提到黄道带
Yeah, you know, when you were saying that the Zodiac...
你说很危险 我在想  真的很危险 而且
You know, when you said it was dangerous, I just thought that it is dangerous, and it's... Stupid?
很蠢? 对 所以我应该打给他太太 问问她有没有任何消息
Stupid And I just thought that I should call his wife and just see if she's heard from him.
我有一些零钱
I have some change.
好了 她说有消息会再打给我
Okay Well, she said she'd call when she heard from him.
很好 对
Good Yeah.
梅乐妮 我应该回家等电话
Melanie, I should really go home and wait for the call.
你该不会想骗我跟你回家吧?
Is this some sleazy plan to get me to go home with you?
什么? 不是!
What? No.
食物就打包好了
I'll get the food to go.
喂!
Hello!
嗨 我约了人在这里见面
Hi! I'm supposed to meet somebody here.
有消息吗?
Anything?
你不用留下来陪我 别开玩笑了
You don't have to stay Are you kidding?
这是我最棒的一次约会
This is the most interesting date I've ever had.
保罗? 罗伯?
Paul? Robert?
是啊 你坐着吗?
Yes You sitting down?
是啊 你绝对不会相信
Yes You're not gonna believe this.
大卫! 离奇的转折 猎物变成猎人
Dave! In a bizarre twist, the hunted has become hunter.
旧金山纪事报 记者 也就是黄道带猎杀目标保罗·艾瑞
San Francisco Chronicle reporter and Zodiac target Paul Avery
声称找到新的线索
claims to have uncovered new information
针对河滨市唯一未破的谋杀案
regarding the only unsolved homicide in Riverside County's history
艾瑞深信 1966年南加州的谋杀案
a 1966 Southern California murder
很可能是黄道带的第一名受害人
that Avery now believes was the Zodiac's first victim.
什么? 他没告诉你吗?
What? He didn't call you about this? Hang on!
等等 我把河滨市凶手寄给媒体的信件
The Riverside killer wrote to the press letters
亲自拿给鉴识专家进行比对
that I then took personally to the Office of Questioned Documents.
专家怎么说?
And what did this expert tell you?
就像我早就知道的答案一样
What I knew in my gut, Ron.
两封信笔迹相同
The handwriting matches Zodiac's.
他怎么拿到河滨市的证物?
How'd he get the evidence out of Riverside?
王八蛋 没想到他会来这招
He took it to Sherwood without telling us, the son of a bitch.
你知道我们有多糗吗? 我们怎么确定这条线索是真的?
You know how bad this looks? Hey, how do we know that this lead is real?
当然是真的 我怎么知道? 因为是从电视上看到的
It's very real You know how I know? Because I saw it on TV.
1970年11月18日
大卫 嗨
Excuse me Dave Hi.
你认识倪梅尔 司法部调查员
Dave, you know Mel Nicolai He's working the case for Justice.
幸会 梅尔
Good to see you, Mel.
谁能告诉我为何我得透过媒体
All due respect, can someone explain to me why I'm reading about breaks in this case
才知道这案子有新的线索?
in the Chronicle instead of getting calls from you?
我们被整了 大卫 少来这套
We got screwed Dave, come on.
你也常上报 民众会提供线索
You do get your name in the paper a lot People talk.
我从来没有公开讨论案情
I don't ever talk about an open investigation, period Okay, Ken?
大卫吗? 嘿 嗨! 保罗·艾瑞
Dave? Hey Hi.
我可以搭你的便车去 ? 保罗 不行
Paul Avery Can I catch a ride with you gents when we get there? Not a good idea, Paul.
去同一个地方还要我搭计程车
He's gonna make me take a cab when we're going to the same place.
感谢您搭乘太平洋西南航空
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you for choosing PSA.
好吧 好吧
Fair enough Fair enough Please take your seats at this time.
请注意 吸烟区在最后六排
Remember, smoking is in the last six aisles only.
祝您旅途愉快
Enjoy your flight.
两小时后 加州 河滨市
克劳斯? 你好 嗯
Cross? Hi Yeah.
我是侦探大卫·托希奇 旧金山警局 你好?
Detective David Toschi, SFPD How are you doing?
好 谢谢你们的协助
Great Thanks for having us down today.
没问题 我听说你给我们带来了些资料
Not at all I hear you have some files for us.
我给你看我的 你给我看你的
I'll show you mine You show me yours.
旧金山是吧? 是的 旧金山
Frisco huh? That's right San Francisco.
纳巴市的肯·那罗 肯
Ken Narlow from Napa Ken.
司法部的梅尔·尼克莱 梅尔
Mel Nicolai, Justice Mel.
这是我们所知道的
Here's what we know.
贝特兹曾就读河滨市社区大学
Cheri Jo Bates attended Riverside Community College.
1966年10月30日那晚 她在图书馆念书
She studies in the library the night of October 30th, 1966.
九点钟关门后她与一名男性离开
She leaves with an unidentified male at closing, 9:00 p.m.
隔天她被发现在停车场 被刺杀身亡
Her body's found the next morning in a parking lot, stabbed to death.
她的车被弄坏
Her car is disabled.
有人把点火器的线路切断, 电池不起作用
Someone cut the coil in the distributor, the battery died.
就有人过来, 假意帮忙
The someone comes back, offers to help.
就像凯瑟琳琼斯那样 谁?
Like Kathleen Johns Who?
莫德斯托郊区的一个女的, 可能是黄道带的受害者
A woman outside of Modesto, might be a Zodiac victim.
可能 可能是 我这里有她的一些资料
Might Might be I have her comp right here in this file.
好的
Okay.
11月29日 案发一个月后
A typewritten confession was sent to the Riverside Press Enterprise
河滨市企业报 收到打字的自白书
on November 29th, a month after Bates's murder.
报社刊登这封自白书
They ran it.
我没有病 我只是疯了 但游戏不会终止
"I'm not sick I am insane But that will not stop the game.
这封信应该公开给大众阅读
"This letter should be published for all to read."
他要公开 他说这是游戏 这可能就是黄道带
He wants to be published He calls it a game I mean, this could be our boy.
半年后 警方 父亲和报社
Six months later, the police, the girl's father, and the paper
都收到了这些信
they all received these.
双倍邮资 黄道带的习惯
Double postage, just like Zodiac.
贝特兹该死
这是莫瑞尔用来比对的信?
These are what Sherwood Morrill matched the Zodiac letters?
除了这些还有这块桌面 唐
These and the desktop Don.
几个月后工友在校园的仓库 发现这块桌面
This was found a couple of months later by a janitor in RCC storage.
切 清洁 如果血液鲜红/清洁 血液泼洒在她的新洋装
莫瑞尔用桌面比对字迹?
Sherwood got a handwriting match off wood?
谁会刻上自己的笔迹?
Who etches in their own handwriting?
老实说 我看不出笔迹很像
To be honest with you, our letters and your letters, I don't see it.
保罗·艾瑞怎么拿到信件的拷贝?
How did Paul Avery get his hands on the exemplars?
是我给他的 前几天打电话聊了一个钟头
I gave them to him We talked on the phone the other day for about an hour.
我告诉他你会来 你跟他说我们要碰面?
And I told him you were gonna be here You told him we were meeting? Yeah.
对 我也说这不是黄道带
I also told him we don't think this is Zodiac.
等等
Okay, wait a minute.
你不觉得这是黄道带? 我们另外锁定一名嫌犯
You don't think this is Zodiac? We got a guy we like for it.
虽然没有足够的证据 不过我很确定凶手就是他
We don't have enough to pin it on him yet, but we're pretty sure it's him.
既然你认为不是黄道带 那干嘛把证物交给艾瑞?
If you don't think this is Zodiac, then why give anything to Avery?
我只是想合作 你合作的方式是  把证物交给记者?
I'm trying to cooperate Oh, that's how you cooperate? By giving information to reporters?
我不懂笔迹 但莫瑞尔很确定
Look, I don't know about the handwriting, but Sherwood says it's a match, right?
就假设你的嫌犯杀了贝特兹 他打了一封自白书
So, let's just say that your guy did Cheri Jo He types the confession.
黄道带在报纸上看到 然后再写信抢功劳
Zodiac reads it in the paper, and he writes a letter taking credit for it.
他干过这种事 现在你有我们所有的证据
Now, that's something he's done before Look, now you have everything we have.
不过我看你们是白跑一趟
But, in my opinion, you guys came south for nothing.
完了 大家 真的完了
FUBAR, gentlemen, FUBAR.
不管怎么说 可能还是黄道带
I don't care what he says This still could be Z.
问题是全加州都这么想吧
The problem is the entire state already thinks it is.
跟你的公关说吧
Well, there's your press agent Talk to him about it.
我不是来惹麻烦的
I come in peace I don't want any trouble.
我懒得理你 保罗 只是尽我的职务
I really don't want to talk to you right now, Paul Not now.
是吗? 你害我办不了案
Just trying to do my job Oh, really? Well, now I can't do mine.
光处理这些线索就够头痛 现在你又吓坏全加州
We're already screwed with the amount of tips we got on this thing, and you just freaked out the entire state.
那帕 瓦列霍 司法部 都怀疑我的能力
I have got Napa, Vallejo, and DOJ looking at me sideways
河滨市则认为我白跑一趟
and Riverside's telling me I'm on a snipe hunt!
贝特兹是我给你的线索
Jesus Hey, Cheri Jo Bates was a gift I gave that to you.
你们俩根本查不出来
You and Armstrong never would have found her.
他可能不是黄道带
This may not be Zodiac Does that matter to you?
你在乎吗? 你可能害河滨市无法起诉嫌犯
What if it is? Does it matter that Riverside may not be able to make a case against their suspect because of you?
我费尽工夫引蛇出洞
Tell it to Sherwood I'm out here, beating the bushes
我们在同一阵线耶 谁跟你同一阵线?
trying to draw him out We're in this together No, we're not in anything together, Paul
我没兴趣增加报纸发行量 他写信给我 威胁我的性命
because I'm not interested in upping my circulation Oh, boy He wrote me He threatened my life.
神探 你查了一年半还抓不到人
Hey, Bullitt! Been a year and a half, you gonna catch this fucking guy or not?
去你的 非常乐意接受
Go fuck yourself Happily.
你应该先告知我的 保罗
You should have called me, Paul.
谢谢
Thank you.
黄道带命案获得新证物 与河滨市命案有关
你看到吗? 看到了
Did you see this? Unfortunately, yes.
全加州的疯子都来了
Here comes every lunatic in California.
我就是黄道带 你是怎么杀害被害人的?
I'm the Zodiac And how did you kill your victims?
用枪 不 用铁捶
With a gun No, with a hammer.
我只能说他仍在政府机构上班
All I'm authorized to tell you is that he's still under government employment.
谁准许你告诉我这些? 我只能说这么多
And who authorized you to tell me this? That's all I'm authorized to say.
只有安德烈
Only a little rat bastard like Andre
会切下被害人的手臂
could have done something like cut off all the victims' hands.
黄道带没有切断任何人的手臂
Zodiac didn't cut off any of the victims' hands.
你确定吗? 是的
Are you sure? Yes, sir.
我跟崔维斯一起工作快十年
Travis and I worked here side by side for 10 years.
命案是从他的脚被辗断后开始的
His foot gets crushed in an accident and the killings begin.
这是巧合吗?
Coincidence? I don't know.
我不知道 你是警察耶 想也知道
You're a cop, man Do the math.
你有想过凶手或许是保罗·艾瑞
Have you considered the killer might be Paul Avery?
常常想
Frequently.
当时他在喝啤酒
He was drinking Coors, getting a load on.
然后聊到猎杀人类 就像那本书一样
Starts talking about hunting people Like that book.
在枪管绑一支手电筒 就能在黑暗中行凶
Says how you can put a light at the end of a gun to use as a sight in the dark.
他这么说吗?
He said that? Yeah.
对啊 所以我就问他" 你打算如何脱罪?"
So I asked him," How would you get away with it?"
然后他说"很简单 因为我没有杀人动机"
And he said," It would be easy" 'cause there'd be no real motive to the thing."
他又说他会写信给警方 自称黄道带恶整警方
Then he said he'd write letters to the police and call himself Zodiac to mess with them.
李喜欢恶整别人 你确定他有说"黄道带" ?
Leigh liked messing with people You're positive he said" Zodiac"? Yeah.
对 我跟他说这称号很蠢
I thought it was a stupid name So I told him.
他生气的说"我不在乎你怎么想"
He got up all upset and said," I don't care what you think.
我想了很久 我要用这称号
"I've thought about it a long time and that's the name I'm gonna use."
你觉得他想了很久吗?
Did you feel like he'd been thinking about it a long time?
他丢掉学校的工作很不爽
He was raw about losing his job at the school.
他说要射破校车的轮胎
He talked about shooting out the tires of a school bus
对那些"可爱的小孩"下手
and picking off the little darlings.
他真的说了这些话? 就是这些话才让我记忆深刻的
He actually used those words? That's what made me remember.
后来我跟老婆说我不想再见到他了 我就没再见过他
Afterwards, I told my wife I didn't wanna see him again And I haven't since.
还有一件事 李喜欢潜水
Other thing is, Leigh's into skin diving.
他去过那座湖好几次
I know he's been up to that lake a bunch of times.
瑞莎湖 你跟他去过吗?
Lake Berryessa? Did you ever go with him?
几次吧 我们也到附近的布达溪钓鱼
Couple times We went fishing by Putah Creek near there.
告诉他你几时想到是他的
Tell him when you put it together.
大约是一年前 在报上开始报导黄道带
About a year ago, in the paper, there was a story about the Zodiac.
我就回想起来了 我试着打给地方警察
And it all comes back I tried to call the local cops.
他们不理他 以为他疯了 你确定
They blew him off Thought he was a nut.
有关黄道带的谈话
And you're sure the conversation you had about Zodiac
是发生在1968年1月1日?
took place on January 1st, 1968?
不可能在那天之后
It couldn't have been any later.
我1月20日要在洛杉矶开始新工作 我得搬家
I started a new job in L.A on January 20th I had to move.
我觉得不是他 这家伙  亚瑟·李·艾伦?
This is my problem This guy... Arthur Leigh Allen?
这个李先生在元旦那天跟一个钓友 透露整个犯案计划?
This guy, Leigh, just lays out his entire evil plan to a fishing buddy on New Year's Day?
也许他很生气 又喝了点酒
I don't know He's angry, he's been drinking
他想了很久 这很合理
been thinking about it for a while I can buy that.
那唐钱尼为什么没早点报警?
So why didn't Cheney contact us sooner?
我查过了 他有
I checked He did.
第一起关于李·艾伦的报案
First recorded contact with the police department about Allen
来自波蒙纳警局1970年 1月10日他的报案没被注意
was in Pomona January 10th, 1970 He just got lost in the shuffle.
李有惹毛唐吗? 比如说搞上唐的老婆?
Did Cheney have anything against Allen? Did Allen screw his wife or anything?
我们会全面调查 不过我觉得这家伙有嫌疑
We're gonna do a full background check But I got to tell you, I like this guy.
那就采集他的字迹吧
So, let's pull some handwriting samples.
嗨 莫瑞尔有样本
Hi I talked to Sherwood He got the samples.
你吃什么? 培根生菜蕃茄三明治
What are you having? BLT.
支票存根联没用 字迹不够多
So, the check stubs are a wash There's not enough handwriting.
申请表的字迹不像黄道带 但是不能证明
The application's got more, but it doesn't look like Z's
他是或不是凶嫌
so he can't rule him in But he can't rule him out, either.
这么说很含糊 他需要更多笔迹样本
Well, that's vague He needs more samples.
还有 这家伙是个变态 当梅尔从泉谷镇拿到申请表
Also, our guy is a pervert When Mel got the application from Valley Springs
他们说李因为乱摸孩童被开除
they told him that Allen had been fired for touching kids.
乱摸? 婉转的说法
Touching? Polite euphemism.
你要怎么做? 打几通电话
So what do you want to do? Make some phone calls.
薯条不吃了吗? 请便
Are you done with the fries? Go ahead.
你们看过黄道带的信件拷贝吗?
Did you and Mr. Cheney have a chance to look at the copies of the Zodiac letters we sent you?
有 有些内容挺变态的 我们知道
Yeah Some of this stuff is pretty creepy.
我是说就像李一样变态
Yeah, we know that I mean, creepy like Leigh.
他故意拼错字 觉得很有趣
He misspells words like that He thinks it's funny.
那么笔迹呢?
What about the handwriting?
我不知道 不是有专家验证吗?
I don't know Don't you have experts for that stuff?
专家说字迹不能证明是同一个人
Our man at Questioned Documents says it's inconclusive.
也许他用另一只手写字
Maybe he did it with his other hand.
那封信写得太工整 不像是用另一只手写的字
The letters are a little too neat for someone to have written with the wrong hand.
但是李就可以 对吧? 什么意思? 他能双手并用
But not for Leigh, right What do you mean? He's ambidextrous.
能用双手写字 你们不知道?
He can write with either hand Didn't you guys know that?
平常艾伦都用左手写字
In everyday life, Allen uses his left hand.
填写工作申请表 写信给朋友
Job applications, letters to friends, et cetera.
但是他用右手写黄道带的信
But he writes the Zodiac letters with his right hand
写出不同的笔迹让人无法比对
producing a different handwriting that he can't be linked to.
我们得去见这家伙 他在哪里?
We got to see this guy, Chief Where is he? Vallejo.
瓦列霍 在皮诺尔的油厂工作 他老哥也在那里工作
He works at Union Oil in Pinole His brother's up there, too.
两个人都见 记得知会穆拉斯 那里是他的辖区
See them both Make sure you call Mulanax It is his backyard.
是啊 河滨市警局就很合作
Oh, right, because that worked so well for us in Riverside.
咱们不计代价乖乖合作
Cooperation, that's us, at all costs.
一天后 加州 罗迪欧 1971年8月4日
你们在这里向他问话 对了 贩卖机坏了
You can talk to him in here Coke machine's busted, by the way.
我去叫他
I'll go get him for you.
你们要怎么进行?
So how do you guys wanna do this?
比尔和密告者谈过 他来发问
Well, Bill talked to the informants He leads, we follow?
我没意见
It's okay by me.
艾伦先生 我是比尔·阿姆斯壮警探
Mr. Allen, I'm Inspector Bill Armstrong.
大卫·陶希警探和杰克·穆拉斯警官
This is Inspector Dave Toschi and Sergeant Jack Mulanax.
我们负责调查发生在旧金山 以及瓦列霍的黄道带杀人事件
We're investigating the Zodiac murders in San Francisco and Vallejo.
请坐
Please, sit down.
密告者说你说了一些话
The informant notified us that you made certain statements
就在黄道带命案的十一个月前
11 months prior to the first Zodiac murder.
是真的话 对你很不利
If they're true, they're quite incriminating.
你记得说过关于这些话的吗? 没有
Do you recall having any such conversation? No Have you ever read
听过或看过黄道带的报导吗?
or heard anything about the Zodiac?
刚上报的时候 不过之后我就没再注意了
When it was first in the paper But I didn't follow it after those first reports.
为什么? 太病态了
Why not? Too morbid I...
我跟另外一位警官也这么说
I told all this to the other officer.
哪一位警官? 瓦列霍来的警官
Which other officer? From Vallejo.
你记得他的名字吗?
Do you remember his name?
不记得 不过就在湖边命案之后
No, but it was right after the murder at the lake.
你跟那位警官说了什么?
And what did you tell this officer?
我说那周末我去了盐岬潜水
I told him that I'd gone to Salt Point that weekend to skin dive.
我一个人去 遇见了一对情侣
That I was alone but I met a couple there.
你们要的话 我家有他们的名字
I have their names at home if you want them.
那就太好了 亚瑟 李
That would be great, Arthur.
什么? 李 没有人叫我亚瑟
Leigh What? Leigh Nobody calls me Arthur.
而且我那天回家 邻居有看见我
Also, that day when I came home, my neighbor saw me.
大约是下午四点吧 不过我忘了跟那位警察说
It was around 4:00 But I forgot to tell the other officer that.
邻居的名字? 比利·怀特
Neighbor's name? Bill White.
他在一星期后左右去世
He died a week or so afterwards.
心脏病 所以我没有打给警察
Heart attack So I didn't think to call to follow up.
车上沾有血迹的那把刀
The knives I had in my car with the blood on them
是我准备晚餐时杀鸡的血迹
that blood came from a chicken that I killed for dinner.
什么? 那个周末我把刀放在车上
What? I had knives in my car that weekend.
也许比尔看到才向警方检举我
Maybe Bill saw them and called the other officer on me.
我们会调查这件事
Well, we'll be checking in on that.
我问你另一件事
Well, let me ask you something else.
你在1966年间去过南加州吗?
Were you ever in Southern California at any time in 1966?
这是关于河滨市谋杀案吗? 没错
Is this about the Riverside killing? Yes.
当时我的确去过那里
Well, I guess I was there around that time.
我以前常去那里 我喜欢看赛车
I used to go down there a lot I like the auto races.
密告者说你能双手并用
Informant says that you're ambidextrous?
这不是真的
No, that's untrue.
你不能用双手写字?
You can't write with both hands?
小时候老师有逼我学 但学不来 我是左撇子
My teachers tried to make me when I was a kid, but I couldn't I'm left handed.
他还说你扬言要杀害学童
He also said that you made statements about killing school children.
太可怕了
That is...
那真是可怕的说法 那真是可怕的说法
That is horrible That is... That's a horrible thing to say.
你从来没有因为你猥亵学童
So, you weren't angry about being fired from Valley Springs
而遭到开除的事感到愤怒?
for touching your students?
我不是黄道带
I'm not the Zodiac.
就算是 也不会告诉你们
And if I was, I certainly wouldn't tell you.
不错的手表
That's a nice watch.
谢谢 我能看吗?
Thank you May I see it?
我能看吗?
May I see it?
哪里买的?
Where'd you get it?
两年前我妈送我的圣诞礼物
It was Christmas gift from my mother two years ago.
你妈真好
That's very sweet.
告诉我 亚瑟
So, tell me something, Arthur.
你不记得和任何人谈过黄道带?
You don't remember anyone you might have had a conversation with regarding the Zodiac?
也许和瓦列霍休闲中心的 泰德或费尔谈过吧
Maybe Ted Kidder or Phil Tucker at Vallejo Recreation.
我不能确定 我在那里上过班
But I couldn't be positive I used to work there when...
最危险的游戏
The Most Dangerous Game.
什么? 最危险的游戏 你们是为了这件事来的 对吧?
What? The Most Dangerous Game That's why you're here, isn't it?
我高中最喜欢的一本书
It was my favorite book in high school.
描述一个人在孤岛 等船难的生还者
It's about this man who waits for people to get shipwrecked on this island.
因为他厌倦猎杀动物 想挑战猎杀人类看看
Because he was tired of hunting animals, he hunted the people for the challenge.
所以"人类比任何猛兽更危险"
And man is the most dangerous animal of all?
这就是整本书的主题
That's the whole point of the story.
很棒的一本书
Great book.
至少我是跟费尔这么说的
Or, at least, that's what I told Phil.
我能走了吗?
May I go?
当然
Sure.
谢谢你的时间 我很乐意协助你们
Thanks for your time I'm willing to help in any way possible.
我很期待有一天
I look forward to the day
当警察不再被称为是猪猡的那一天
when police officers are no longer referred to as pigs.
谢了
Thanks.
我们会再联络
We'll be in touch.
有谁觉得他还需要被调查吗?
So does anyone think this suspect warrants further investigation?
这些是黄道带信件的副本
These are copies of some of the Zodiac letters that were sent.
请你们看一看
We'd like you to take a look at them.
你们认为我弟弟是黄道带
You think my brother's the Zodiac.
我们正在调查他 你们会逮捕他吗?
Well, we're looking at him Are you going to arrest him?
艾伦太太 我们不会因为 调查一个人而逮捕他
Mrs Allen, we don't arrest people just because we're interested in them.
李一向都有心理问题 他猥亵学童的事是真的吗?
Well, Leigh's always been troubled Is it true about the children?
很不幸是的 我们知道后就很少去见他
Unfortunately We don't see him much anymore since we found out.
你们觉得唐·钱尼怎样?
What are your feelings about Don Cheney?
唐·钱尼? 我旧室友?
Don Cheney? My old roommate?
是他连络你们的? 这是机密
Was he the one who contacted you? That's confidential.
唐这个人很可靠
Well, Don's a very reliable guy.
他说的话 我会相信是真的
If he were to tell you something, I'd believe it to be true.
这个字 怎么样?
This one What about it?
他用两个S拼圣诞节
Here, where he spells" Christmas" with two" S's."
两年前我们收到他的圣诞卡
We got a Christmas card from Leigh a couple years ago.
也是同样的拼法
He spelled it the exact same way Christ mass.
那张圣诞卡还在吗? 我可以找找看
"Chr i s t mass" Would you still have that? I can look for it.
谢谢 太好了
Thank you That'd be great.
我们还能帮什么忙?
Is there anything else we can do to help?
下次李出门时他老哥会搜他房间
The brother said he would search Leigh's apartment next time he went out of town.
这样就不必申请搜票 就这一次
That gets you around a warrant For the time being.
如果找到什么 穆拉斯会去找瓦列霍检察官 仔细搜查房子
If we do find something, Mulanax will go to the DA in Vallejo, and we could search the place properly.
我去找贝瑞莎命案两天后 向李问过话的警官
Now I got a chance to talk to the cop who interviewed Leigh Allen two days after the Berryessa murders.
他不记得为什么要问他话 不过他认为李不像杀人凶手 所以没有继续追查
Doesn't remember how he got onto him, but didn't think he looked like a killer so he didn't like him for Z.
你认为他是凶手? 我很想当场就逮捕他
But you do? I wish I could've taken the guy in there.
别急 大卫 多找些线索给莫瑞尔
Take it slow, Dave Try and find more stuff for Sherwood.
笔迹符合的话就罪证确凿
A match'll get us farther on the warrants.
艾瑞在二线 叫他去死
Avery's on two Tell him to screw.
你要我直接说还是加点料?
You want me to communicate that verbatim or can I spice it up a little?
真要命
Christ, kid.
怎么了
Yeah.
保罗 我在想... 噢 上帝保佑
Paul, I've been thinking... Oh, God save us all.
给梅尔文的信
The letter to Melvin Belli
是路口谋杀案一年后寄出的
was sent exactly one year after the Lake Herman Road murder.
一封给贝特兹的父亲的信
And the one to Cheri Jo Bates' father
是在她死后六个月寄出的
was sent exactly six months after her death.
她在万圣节前一天被杀 是的
She was killed a day before Halloween Yeah.
你也收到了万圣节贺卡...
And you received a Halloween card...
要知道 这些都是很吸引人的新闻 罗伯特
You know, these are all fascinating pieces of news, Robert
不过稍早了点
it's a bit early in the day.
保罗 11点了我们错过了编辑部会议
Paul, it's 11:00 and we missed Editorial.
对不起 我不是有意叫你的 没关系
I'm sorry I didn't mean to wake you up No, no, no.
我只是在想... 好了好了
I just thought that... No, no, no.
这名嫌犯不是黄道带
This suspect is not your Zodiac.
样本符合支票及申请表的笔迹?
This sample matches the canceled checks and the application?
他能双手并用  完全符合 我们重新测试他的左手
Perfectly So we've just retested the left hand I mean, we know he's ambidextrous.
38年来 我没看过有人双手笔迹完全不同
In 38 years, I've never seen anyone that ambidextrous.
一定会有相同之处
Both hands would have commonalities.
抱歉 这论点无法成立
I'm sorry Just not gonna work.
重案组 我是陶希 大卫 我是杰克·穆拉斯
Homicide, Toschi Dave, it's Jack Mulanax.
嗨 怎么样?
Hey Mulanax Yeah.
法官不愿意发出搜查令
We struck out with the judge He won't sign off on a warrant for Allen's house.
为什么? 他说证据不足
Why not? Said it wasn't enough.
除非找到符合的笔迹和证物
Now, unless we bring him a handwriting match or some evidence that...
没有搜查令怎么找到证物?
How are we gonna get evidence if we can't toss the house?
不知道
I don't know.
真的很抱歉 不 谢谢你
I truly am sorry No, no Thank you, Jack.
你想怎么办? 没有瓦列霍的证物就没辙
What do you wanna do? Don't know what I can do without Vallejo.
我们需要李的右手笔迹 没有就拿不到搜查令
We need Allen's right hand We can't get it without a warrant.
还有其他的嫌犯吗?
Are there other guys you should be looking at?
至少还有多少  两千三百个
Only, what? Twenty three hundred?
好吧 就这样了
Okay, then.
保罗 你写信给司法部
Paul, you wrote the Justice Department
要求负责调查黄道带命案?
asking to be put in charge of the Zodiac investigation?
一年后 加州 旧金山
我只是建议  你用报社的信纸?
I merely suggested... On our letterhead?
对案情熟悉的个人或单位
that those with intimate knowledge of the case create an information clearinghouse
能够聚集在一起交换线索和想法
to promote an exchange and free flow of ideas.
然后由你来主导 还有谁比我更适合?
And that you run it Well, who better than me?
被黄带道盯上的男人
The marked man.
你想继续在报社工作 得答应我三件事 第一 戒酒
Paul, if you want to work here, I need three things One, stop boozing.
第二 停止你目前在做的事
Two, stop doing whatever else it is you're doing.
第三 忘了你这种荒谬的想法
And three, cut this nonsense out.
亲爱的丹波顿 如果你认为
Sweetest of Templetons, if at any time
我杰出的工作表现 在这鬼地方不适用的话
you feel my excellent work is no longer in step with this trashy provincial rag
我倒是很乐意
I'll more than happily...
寻求其它的发展
More than happily decamp for greener pastures.
保罗 我是认真的
Paul, I mean it!
保罗? 是
Paul? Yep.
刚刚是怎么回事? 编辑部的斗争
What was that? An editorial tête à tête
要喝一杯吗? 现在是早上十点耶
Wanna grab a drink? It's 10:00 in the morning.
也许可以算是早午餐 保罗
Late breakfast? Early lunch, or... Paul.
你还好吗?
Are you okay?
不好
No.
多谢你的慰问
Thank you for asking.
矮子 是 出去喝一杯吧 保罗 你要去哪里?
Shorty! Let's go out for one Paul, where are you going?
你们停止调查我小叔?
So, you moved off my brother in law?
我们申请不到搜查令
We couldn't get a warrant.
1972年9月7日 加州 瓦列霍
去年我们安排李和社工见面
Last year we arranged for Leigh to get help from a social worker.
他只去了两次
He only went twice.
最近我婆婆带他来看小孩 这是九个月来第一次见面
We saw him recently for the first time in nine months My mother in law brought him by to see the new baby.
后来我就去找社工了解状况
After he left, I went to see that social worker.
他不能透露病人病情 我就直接问他
He couldn't talk about a former patient, so I just asked him straight out
李会不会杀人
if he thought Leigh was capable of killing people.
由于病人保密法则 社工说他会杀人
Because of patient confidentiality... The man said yes.
你们为什么九个月没见过他? 他在圣塔罗莎的学校上课
Why hadn't you seen him in nine months? He's going to school in Santa Rosa.
圣塔罗莎? 他住在哪里? 他的拖车屋
Santa Rosa? Where is he living? In his trailer.
在圣塔罗莎? 索诺犸郡
In Santa Rosa? Sonoma County.
我们不用透过瓦列霍检察官
We wouldn't have to go through the Vallejo DA.
你们有11个月没问过他话 现在要去搜他的拖车屋?
It's been 11 months since you talked to this guy, and now you wanna search his trailer?
能找到证物最好
If we find something, great.
不然也能采到指纹和双手的笔迹
If not, we get his prints and handwriting samples from both hands.
我以为莫瑞尔推翻了你的论点
I thought Sherwood shut you down.
我想请别人鉴定
What if I can get a second opinion?
我不想反驳莫瑞尔的鉴定 我是他一手栽培的
I don't wanna step on Sherwood's toes He trained me at this.
我只想知道嫌犯能不能双手并用
Terry, all I need to know is if the suspect is ambidextrous.
他是不是可能用另一只手写信
Could he possibly have written those letters with his other hand?
我只告诉你
Between you and me?
笔迹鉴定有不同的学派
Because there are differing schools of thought on this.
只要拿到他另一只手的笔迹 如果他是黄道带就会符合
Get the samples of his other hand If he's the Zodiac, you'll get a match.
这是泰瑞目前的想法
That's the current thinking, according to Terry Pascoe.
我也问了愿意作证的心理医师
Meanwhile, I spoke to a psychologist who'd be willing to testify
他说像黄道带这种性格多变的人
that someone who undergoes a personality change like Zodiac
生理上也会改变 比如改变笔迹
would manifest it physically, altering his handwriting.
所以莫瑞尔的笔迹鉴定会不符合
Which is why Sherwood couldn't get a match from Allen's samples.
泰瑞 心理医师和钱尼夫妇
We got Terry Pascoe, this psychology guy
有他们就能申请搜查令
coupled with Cheney... It could be enough for a warrant.
请钱尼做正式笔录
Get Cheney on the record.
他就会自称为黄道带
"And that he would call himself Zodiac."
是的 你愿意在  高等法庭发誓作证?
Yes And you're willing to swear to this, under oath, in Superior Court?
毫不会犹豫
Without any hesitation.
非常感谢你 钱尼先生
Thank you very much, Mr. Cheney Thank you very much for your time.
嫌犯名叫亚瑟·李·艾伦 谢谢你
Thank you Suspect is Arthur Leigh Allen.
家住加州圣塔罗莎日落拖车公园
Lives in Sunset Trailer Court in Santa Rosa, California.
体貌特征:
Physical description.
艾伦高大 体型粗壮
Allen is similar in height, weight and build
与贝湖行刺案所描述的案犯特征一致
to a man seen at Lake Berryessa on the day of the stabbings.
但是 他和加州的那个案子体貌描述不一样
I understand he doesn't look much like the San Francisco composite.
是的 高大粗壮只是粗略描述
True Height and weight are sketchy
但是从都是粗壮的白种人这点看是一致的
but lumbering Caucasian with a crew cut is right on.
我们对从孩子口中得到的口供并没有多少信心
We never had much confidence in the composite from the kids.
那晚说是见到黄道带的巡警
The patrolman who say Zodiac that night
说他和草图上的并不相像
said he didn't look much like the sketch.
军用靴鞋印
Military boot prints.
艾伦入过海军 穿10号半的鞋
Allen was in the Navy Wears a size 10 and a half.
与贝湖案的大小一致
Same size as the prints found at Berryessa.
那枪呢?
What about gun?
切尼说他有好几种武器 我们会在搜捕令中写明
Cheney says Allen owns several firearms We'll list them in the warrant.
密码呢 可能是在海军中学到的
And the ciphers Could be code training in the Navy
也有人作证说艾伦过去画过
and people have seen Allen with ciphers in the past.
真的吗? 谁?
Really? Who?
他的嫂子及他的哥哥叫做费尔塔克
That would be his sister in law and a man named Phil Tucker
他哥哥在瓦列霍的公共泳池工作
that he worked with at a public pool in Vallejo.
费尔塔克还告诉我们他和弟弟曾
And Phil Tucker told us about a conversation that he had with Allen
把手电装到枪管上
about how to attach a flashlight to the barrel of a gun.
从密码和手电上就给了我们2个证据
That gives us two sources on the ciphers and two on the flashlight.
那他对孩子的恐吓呢?
What about his threats on children?
嫌犯曾在小学工作
Suspect worked for elementary schools
因为猥亵于1968年3/4月间被开除
and was fired for molestation in March, April '68.
这可能给他以动机 至少 这是家庭因素
Could give him motive At the very least, it's home turf.
从他的恐吓信2个主要环节看
He'd have knowledge of bus routes
他对校车路线很熟悉
which the two major threats centered around.
炸弹呢?
What about the bomb?
艾伦的工作是化学师
Allen works as a chemist.
还对地理相当熟悉
Take him through the geography.
瓦列霍谋杀犯
Vallejo murders.
艾伦在瓦列霍曾和他妈妈 在她的地下室居住
Allen lives in Vallejo with his mother in her basement.
贝湖案 2个人被刺的那天
Berryessa murder On the day that the two kids were stabbed
他的邻居发现在他的车里有带血的匕首
his neighbor saw bloody knives in his truck
不过他的解释是用来杀鸡了
which he claimed were used to kill a chicken.
他辩解了?
Does he have any alibis?
是的 但是要不是他见过
He claimed he did, but he's been unable to produce the names
他不可能编造对 贝湖案那对情侣的名字
of the couple he supposedly met on the day of Berryessa.
底线是艾伦不可能会辩解全部事
The bottom line is that Allen can't alibi up on anything.
滨河 瓦列霍 湖或者我们
Riverside, Vallejo, the lake or us.
你要不要说说名字的事? 什么名字?
You want to tell me about the name? What name?
黄道带
Zodiac.
艾伦戴的手表不但有那个单词 还有那个十字图案
Allen wears a watch that bears both the word and crosshair symbol.
他还向切尼提起过
And he mentioned Zodiac to Cheney
事情发生一年半之前在任何信件中都可以看到
a year and a half before it appeared in any letter.
约翰... 非常好 伙计们
John... That's pretty good, guys.
我们也是这么想的 让我们把他绳之以法吧
We think so, too Let's take it to a judge.
1972年9月14日 加州 圣塔罗莎 日落拖车公园A-7号
艾伦先生?
Mr. Allen?
圣塔罗莎警局 我们有搜查令
This is the Santa Rosa Police Department We have a warrant to search your residence.
有人吗?
Hello?
我去问附近的邻居
I'll check with the neighbors.
关门 关门
Close the door.
有鼠类动物跑来跑去
Close the door, there's rodents running around.
邻居说他半小时前闪人了
Neighbor said he tore out of here about a half hour ago.
有人向他告密? 他回来前我们不会走
You think somebody tipped him? We're not leaving till he comes back.
我去查后面
I'll check the back.
老天 什么? 松鼠
Jesus What? Squirrels.
这家伙超变态的
Piece of work, this guy.
不只一件 两件蓝色风衣
Not one, but two blue windbreakers.
史坦命案现场那件? 我们会送去验血比对
Like the Stine scene? We'll have those checked for blood.
还有一对黑色手套
And a pair of black gloves.
男性七号大小 跟计程车上那对一样
Men's seven, just like the ones we found in the cab.
鞋子和手套的尺寸也符合
Well, he's got the same size shoes and gloves as Z.
搞不好只是巧合
Probably just a coincidence.
我找到一把枪 你看 不对 是两把枪
Dave, I got a gun Check that Two guns.
两把点22口径手枪 一把自动手枪 一把左轮手枪
They're both .22s One automatic, one revolver.
这倒很有趣
Well, that's interesting.
他的衣橱也有一把M1步枪
Because he happens to have an M 1 rifle here in the closet.
向那些可爱的学童下手
For little darlings bouncing off buses.
有人来了
Someone's here.
哈啰 亚瑟 记得我们吗?
Hello, Arthur Remember us?
没有证据 笔迹呢?
No On the handwriting?
弹道 指纹跟笔迹都不符合
Ballistics, no match Prints, no match Writing, no match.
双手的笔迹吗? 双手的笔迹我们都有
On both hands, right? Because we got handwriting from both his hands.
双手笔迹都不符合
And neither hand matches.
别管莫瑞尔 问其他专家的意见 两位 他不是凶手
Forget Sherwood Let's get another opinion Fellas, he's not your guy.
可恶
Damn it.
嘿!
Hey.
你想怎样? 休息一阵子?
What do you want? Time off?
抱一下?
A hug?
你知道最糟的是什么吗?
Do you know what the worst part of this is?
我不知道我是认为凶手就是艾伦
I can't tell if I wanted it to be Allen so bad
还是希望案子快点结束
because I actually thought it was him, or I just want all this to be over.
因为你认为是他 我也是啊
It's because you thought it was him And I did, too.
这样吧 休息一阵子
You know what? Take some time off.
陪陪你老婆还有小孩
Spend some time with your wife and the kids.
带他们看球赛或是看电影
Go to Candlestick See a movie.
致旧金山市民 我很乐意每天杀一个人
"To the city of San Francisco, I will enjoy killing one person every day
直到你们付我十万元
"until you pay me $100 000.
同意的话 明天早上回覆
"If you agree, say so tomorrow morning
刊登在 旧金山纪事报 交友专栏
"in the personal column San Francisco Chronicle
我就会出面
"and I will set up meeting.
如果得不到回覆
"If I do not hear from you
我会先杀死一名天主教神父 或是
"it will be my next pleasure to kill a Catholic priest or a...
一个黑鬼
"天蝎座"
" ...Scorpio."
他一定是疯了
Who's out of their minds?
我得闪人
I've got to get out of here.
我要去哪里生出十万元?
Where the hell does he expect me to find $100 000?
市长 你不会真要付钱吧?
You're not thinking of paying him, are you, Mr. Mayor?
旧金山市政府不会付钱给凶手 好让他不去杀人
The city of San Francisco does not pay criminals not to commit a crime.
紧急追捕令
长官 是谁负责这一切? 是卡拉汉警探 他在外面等
凶手最后胸口被开了一枪
The killer gets shot in the chest.
结局就是这样 我认识你吗?
That's how it ends Do I know you?
我是罗伯·葛雷史密斯 保罗·艾瑞 纪事报 的同事
I'm Robert Graysmith I work at the Chronicle with Paul Avery.
大卫·陶希 幸会
Dave Toschi Nice to meet you.
那个卡拉汉对你的案子办得不错
Dave! That Harry Callahan did a hell of a job with your case.
是啊 他才不鸟正规的手续对吧?
Yeah No need for due process, right?
你在报社做什么? 我画漫画
What do you do at the Chronicle? I'm a cartoonist.
不错啊 你会逮到他的
That's nice You're gonna catch him.
老弟 这案子都拍成电影了
Pal, they're already making movies about it.
今天我们达成一项协议
We today have concluded an agreement
给光荣的越南结束战争带来和平
to end the war and bring peace with honor in Vietnam.
查尔斯·曼森 是泰特拉比安卡案的头号罪犯...
Charles Manson for the Tate La Bianca mass murders...
在乔奇拉获罪 拐骗案
Guilty in the Chowchilla kidnapping case.
谋杀审判...
In the murder trial of one...
毛主席今天逝世...
Chairman Mao died today...
完全的宽恕 向查尔斯·尼克松...
an absolute pardon unto Richard Nixon...
不 我不是骗子... ...世代仇视...
No, I'm not a crook... ...Generation of hostility...
带来了死亡 有5万美国人
has now led to the death of 50 000 Americans
还有几十万 越南人...
and several hundred thousand Vietnamese...
帕特里夏·哈斯特 被美国共生解放军绑架...
Patricia Hearst is kidnapped by the Symbionese Liberation Army...
我们每个人都要站起来 说"不再"
All of us should stand up together and say," No more."
你的独立宣言 传播开来...
Your Declaration of Independence spreads that...
美国钦佩英国...
Americans admire the United Kingdom...
胡佛先生消失了
Mr. Hoffa has disappeared.
如果我们轻视我们自己的政府...
If we despise our own government...
警察逮到了那个人
that the police have captured a man
四年后 他们去相信 当什么" 山姆之子..."
whom they believe to be the" Son of Sam..."
嗨 我们没见过面 我是罗伯·葛雷史密斯
Hi We haven't met I'm Robert Graysmith.
我是达菲·詹宁
I'm Duffy Jennings.
幸会 彼此彼此
Nice to meet you Good to meet you, man.
这办公桌不错 前一任记者非常优秀
You got a great desk Guy who used to work here was a great reporter.
我猜也是吧 从 旧金山纪事报
Oh, yeah Oh, I'm sure he was I mean, it's a honor to leave the Chronicle
跳槽到 沙加缅度蜜蜂报
and go work for the Sacramento Bee.
算是降级了 对吧?
Dare to dream, right, Robert?
幸会了 彼此彼此
Nice to meet you Nice to meet you, too.
我就坐在美工部
I'm just right down there at the Art department
需要帮忙就说一声
if you need anything, Duffy Yeah.
你确定今晚不用车 比尔? 换你开了
You sure you don't want the car, Bill? It's your turn.
送我回家然后把车开走
You could just drop me off at my place and take the car.
车子你留着吧
You should keep the car.
真的吗?
Yeah?
明天我不来警局了
I'm not coming in tomorrow.
这是怎么回事?
Why? What's up?
我不玩了
I'm done.
我申请调职
I put in for a transfer.
调去哪里? 诈欺组
Where? Looking at Fraud.
我不能再随时待命了
I can't be on call anymore.
我想看着我的孩子长大
I wanna see these kids grow up.
这样也好 比尔
Hey, good for you, Bill.
你会没事的 是啊 我不会有事
You'll be okay Yeah I'll be fine.
嘿!
Hey
我没留下烂摊子给你吧
I'm not leaving you holding the bag on anything, am I?
没啦
No.
那就好
Okay.
知道吗?
Hey, you know what?
也许你可以试试日本料理 生鱼片之类的
Maybe you'll have a chance to try your Japanese food, the raw stuff.
是啊
Yeah.
"我已杀了七人" 黄道带扬言杀害圣荷西女孩
黄道带命案最新线索
确定和黄道带有关
"我不是保罗·艾瑞"
I'm not Paul Avery.
去哄儿子们睡觉 顺便替宝宝换尿布
The boys need to be tucked in, please, and the baby needs changing.
掷硬币决定 想得美
I'll flip you for it You wish.
没人比你有更多黄道带的资料了
Nobody has more Zodiac crap than you do.
搜寻黄道带四件凶器
保罗·艾瑞撰写
不会吧? 嗨 保罗
Are you kidding me? Hi, Paul.
允许你上船
Permission to come aboard It's right there.
坐那里 反正你穿着鞋子 坐那里最好
Anyway, you got shoes on This is perfect right here.
就是这里 好
That's the one Okay.
看到没 超炫的
See that? Mesmerizing Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
我小孩肯定会想要那玩意
My own kids would kill me for one of those.
你还好吗? 棒极了
How are you? Fantastic.
我承认 蜜蜂报 没有 纪事报 来得有趣
I mean, admittedly, the Bee ain't exactly the Chron, but fuck it, right?
来一杯吗? 我没有蓝色的酒
Do you want a drink? I don't have anything blue, but I got...
算了 别麻烦了
Don't worry about that Don't worry about it.
一点都不麻烦 反正没人来过
It's no bother at all Nobody comes by from the old days.
干杯
Cheers.
为咱们俩的健康敬一杯 我的
To your health and mine.
主要是我的啦
Mostly mine.
有什么新鲜事?
So, what's new?
我在想 应该有人写本书
I've been thinking Yeah Somebody should write a book.
早就该有人写本书
Somebody should write a fucking book, that's for sure.
写什么? 黄道带的案子
About what? About Zodiac.
这不是什么新鲜事
It's not new.
我在想只要把所有线索兜在一块
I've been thinking that if you put all the information together
也许会有什么新发现
maybe you could jog something loose.
没有人比你更了解整件案子 那倒是真的
And then I was thinking that nobody knows the case better than you Yeah That's true.
你有档案 认识每个人
You know all the players, and you have all the files.
档案没了 你弄丢了?
Lost them You lost them?
还是扔了 我不知道 我人都搬到船上了
Or I tossed them I don't know I moved onto a boat.
你应该知道我们是跑每日新闻
You know that we work in the daily business, right? As in, today.
干嘛管那老掉牙的新闻?
What do you think we were doing back then?
东湾每三个月死于车祸的人
Do you know that more people die in the East Bay commute
都比那疯子杀的人多
every three months than that idiot ever killed?
他杀了几个人 写了几封信 然后就这样消失了
He offed a few citizens, he wrote a few letters, and he faded into a footnote.
我又没笨到坐在这里等你来
Not that I haven't been sitting here idly
让我重拾人生意义
waiting for you to drop by and reinvigorate my sense of purpose.
那是四年前的事 忘了吧
It was four years ago Let it fucking go.
你错了 这件事很重要
You're wrong It was important.
那你到底做了什么?
Then, what did you ever do about it?
真的那么重要 你却啥都没做
If it was so fucking important, what did you ever do?
你搜我的桌子 翻我的垃圾
You hovered over my desk, you stole from wastebaskets.
我有对你翻脸吗?
Am I being unkind?
我忘了 你都去图书馆
Oh, that's right, I forgot You went to the library.
抱歉打扰你
I'm sorry I bothered you.
嗨 嗨
Hey, hi Hi.
你去了哪里? 图书馆
Where you been? The library.
1977年10月11日 加州 旧金山 华盛顿与樱桃街转角处
谢谢你
Thank you!
陶希警探? 请等一下
Inspector Toschi? Yeah? One moment, please.
嗨 嗨
Hi Hi.
我们在戏院见过面
We met at the movies once.
那一定是在变魔术 我是罗伯葛雷史密斯
It must have been magical I'm Robert Graysmith I work at the Chronicle.
在 旧金山纪事报 工作 能请你吃顿午餐吗?
I was wondering if I could buy you lunch.
好啊 有何不可?
Sure, why not?
你是保罗·艾瑞的朋友?
So, you're a friend of Paul Avery's?
我是为了他来找你的
He's actually the reason I'm here.
我想请教黄道带的案子
I wanted to ask you about Zodiac.
多谢了 不过我们不准讨论案情
Well, I appreciate the interest, but we don't discuss open cases.
那警方每天都在做什么?
Oh, well, what's going on with it, day to day?
积极调查任何线索
We're actively pursuing all leads.
案子就剩你一个人在办
And you're the only one on it, right?
葛雷史密斯先生
Mr. Graysmith
黄道带有三年没有写过信
Zodiac hasn't written in three years.
你知道之后旧金山发生几起命案?
You know how many murders we've had in San Francisco since then?
不知道 200起以上
No Over 200.
有很多死者和家属需要帮助
That's a lot of dead people and grieving families that need our help.
所以已经没有人在乎了
So, nobody cares.
不好意思 我很在乎
Excuse me? I care.
我可以给你看样东西吗?
Okay Can I show you something?
我针对第一张密码做了研究
I've been doing research on the first cipher.
对解码有兴趣的业余人士 都能在这些书里找到解答
Everything an amateur would need to create it can be found in these books.
我在想如果追踪这些书的去向
Now, I started thinking that if you can track these books
也许就能找到凶手
then maybe you can track the man.
你说过黄道带有可能是军人
So, I remember you thought that Zodiac was military
我跑遍所有的军事基地图书馆
so I went to every base library and I got a list of every person
列出借过这些书的人的名字 最后发现一件事
who's ever checked out these books and that's when I found this.
遗失 表示这些书是被偷走
Missing It means they were stolen.
普西迪图书馆的密码书都被偷走
So, almost every book on ciphers was stolen from the Presidio Library?
还有奥克兰陆军图书馆
And the Oakland Army Terminal Library.
有人不想被查到他借了这些书
Somebody didn't want a record of ever having checked out these books.
你是谁?
Who are you again?
我只想帮忙
I just wanna help.
我不能让你帮忙
I can't allow you to help.
不能和你讨论案情 提供资料
I can't discuss the case with you.
更不能叫你去那帕找肯恩·纳尔罗
I can't give you information, and I certainly couldn't tell you to go see Ken Narlow in Napa.
纳 尔 罗
N A R L O W.
很抱歉 葛雷史密斯先生 我们不跟作家合作
I'm sorry, Mr. Graysmith, but we don't cooperate with writers.
我不是作家 是漫画家
Well, I'm not a writer, I'm a cartoonist.
大卫·陶希叫你来 对
And Dave Toschi sent you? Yes.
为什么?
Why? Maybe he...
也许他认为我帮得上忙
Maybe he thought that I could do some good.
你是童子军吗? 第一级鹰级童子军
What are you, some kind of boy scout? Eagle Scout, actually, first class.
你想查就尽管查
Well, if you wanna do this, don't let me stop you.
先去找瓦列霍的杰克·穆拉斯
Better start with Vallejo, Jack Mulanax.
我知道你想干嘛
I understand what you're trying to do.
但这是警方的公开调查
But this is an open police investigation.
我是大卫·陶希的朋友
I'm a friend of Dave Toschi's.
他说你能帮助我
And he said that you might be able to help.
案子没进展 凶手早就走人了
I mean, the case is dead Zodiac's long gone.
他是昨日新闻了 对吗?
He's yesterday's news, right?
他们是这么说的
That's what they say.
所以你有什么损失呢?
So, what's the harm?
不准带纸笔
No pens, no paper.
想知道的就记在脑子里
Anything that you see that's relevant, you got to remember in your head.
了解
Okay.
好 来吧 哪一个?
Okay, here we go Which one? All of them.
全部都是 隔壁有更多 全部都有编号
And there's more in the next room They're all marked with these numbers.
243 146 你不抽烟吧?
243 146 You don't smoke, do you?
高中抽过一次
Once In high school.
这是什么?
What's this?
谢啦
Thank you.
档案243 146
黛琳费伦
与男友在蓝石泉
老兄 你差点吓死我们
Man, you really creeped us out.
9厘米
"Nine millimeter.
"一言不发就开枪"
"Said nothing and began firing."
亚瑟·李·艾伦
最危险的游戏
"Most Dangerous Game.
别因为笔迹不合排除嫌疑
"Do not eliminate this suspect because of handwriting" Not because of handwriting.
"黛琳的姐姐 琳达 对方呼吸沉重 乔治"
"Darlene's sister, Linda" It was all just deep breathing George.
"那是个怪人 怪人"
"It was a strange man George Strange man."
感激不尽
Thank you so much.
公事包 谢啦
Oh, briefcase Oh, thanks.
嗨 杰克 嗨 巴渥
Hey, Jack Hey, Bawart.
那是谁? 葛雷史密斯
Who's that? That's Graysmith.
漫画家 认为他能够破案
Some cartoonist Thinks he's gonna solve the Zodiac.
很好呀
Well, good for him.
交通事故应该不会影响 大部分的开车族
37号高速公路在瓦列霍和 纳伐洛之间有事故
一辆油罐车在今晚翻车
黛琳被跟踪 害怕乔治·瓦特?
匿名电话
开枪当晚
丈夫 公公
沉重的呼吸声
谢谢你跟我见面 我不是来跟你见面的
Thank you for meeting me, Inspector No We're not meeting, Robert.
我们只是碰巧一起坐在这里
We're just two guys who happen to be sitting on the same bench at the same time.
你只有五分钟 我还得回总部
I've got five minutes I've got to get back to the Hall.
就你所知 你在进行调查时
Okay As far as you know, did anyone ever get in touch
有人找过麦克·梅休 让他看嫌犯的照片吗? 为什么?
with Mike Mageau during your investigation and show him suspect photos? Why?
他是唯一看过黄道带的生还者
Well, he's the only surviving victim who ever saw Zodiac without a mask.
你为什么要问我? 梅休和黛琳案隶属瓦列霍管辖
No, I mean, why are you asking me? Mageau and Darlene, that's Vallejo's case.
我只调查保罗史坦 剩四分钟
Paul Stine is mine You've got four minutes now.
黛琳·费伦曾被跟踪
Darlene Ferrin was being followed.
我知道穆拉斯锁定一名嫌犯 乔治·瓦特
Now, I know Mulanax says that they already found this guy, a George Waters?
黛琳在餐馆也有很多仰慕者
But he also said that she had a lot of admirers who would come to the restaurant where she worked.
她很有人缘 的确是
She was popular Very.
后来她和老公搬到新家
Yeah So... She and her husband, they move into their new house
有天晚上他们办了油漆派对
and one night they throw this painting party.
什么是油漆派对? 一堆朋友来帮忙油漆的派对
And what's a painting party? It's a party where people come and help you paint.
听起来很烂
Sounds like a terrible party.
不过 假设来的人并不是瓦特
Well, supposedly, somebody who's not Waters shows up.
而且黛琳很怕他
And Darlene is terrified of him.
你认为黛琳认识黄道带
So you think that Darlene knew Zodiac?
他认识黛琳 或许梅休也认识他
And if Zodiac knew Darlene, then maybe Mageau knows Zodiac.
有可能 但是梅休落跑了
Maybe But Mageau's gone.
你想靠黛琳找到黄道带 就要用别的方法
So if you wanna connect Darlene to Zodiac, you're gonna have to find another way.
我有别的方法 黛琳被谋杀当晚的通联纪录
I have another way Phone calls the night of Darlene's murder.
黄道带有打给警方 不 大卫 当晚还有四通电话
Yeah, Zodiac called the police No, Dave, there were four other calls.
两通打到黛琳的家 一通打给黛琳小叔 一通打给她公公
There were two to Darlene's house, one to Darlene's brother in law
只有沉重的呼吸声 电话从半夜一点半开始打
and one to Darlene's father in law Just heavy breathing They started around 1:30 a.m
当时黛琳家人不知道她已遇害
and this was before anyone in the family knew that Darlene had been shot.
这全在瓦列霍的档案 是的
This was in the Vallejo files? Yeah.
可恶 这并非完全是巧合吧?
God damn it It's got to be more than just a coincidence, right?
黛琳被害的九十分钟后 全家人都接到
I mean, somebody doesn't just randomly prank phone call a victim's entire family
同一通恶作剧电话
90 minutes after they were shot.
所以黄道带不是随机杀死那对情侣 然后才认出黛琳
So, either Zodiac shoots a random couple, then he recognizes Darlene...
就是他故意杀死黛琳的
Or Darlene was shot on purpose.
无论如何 黄道带一定认识黛琳
Either way, Zodiac had to have known Darlene.
非常好 罗伯
That's good, Robert.
既然找不到梅休 或许我可以找黛琳的姐姐
So, I can't find Mageau, so maybe I can find Darlene's sister.
也许她知道神秘男子是谁
And maybe she can tell me who this mystery man is.
试试看 我得走了 她很可爱
Try that I've got to go She's very cute.
很有趣 你提到黄道带打到被害者家里
You know, it's interesting that you should mention Zodiac calling people at home.
他在旧金山也干过一次 什么? 他打给谁?
He did that in San Francisco once What? Who did he call?
不能说 这是机密
I can't tell you That's privileged information.
也许梅尔文·贝利能告诉你
But maybe Melvin Belli could.
梅尔文·贝利 该怎么联络他?
Melvin Belli How do I get to Melvin Belli?
他马上就会回家了 没关系
He should be along soon Oh, that's all right.
我才等了两个小时 他通常不会这么晚回家
I've really... I've only been waiting two hours, so... He's usually not this late.
饼干 谢谢 看起来很好吃
Oh, cookies Thank you These look great.
你是来谈公事吗? 我在写一本关于黄道带的书
You are here on business? I'm writing a book about the Zodiac.
我记得他 我跟他谈过
I remember that I spoke to him.
你跟贝利先生谈过黄道带案? 不是 黄道带打过电话来
You mean to Mr. Belli about the case? No, to the Zodiac when he called.
他说那天是他的生日 非得杀人不可
He said he had to kill because it was his birthday.
等一下 他说那天是他生日?
He said it... Wait He said it was his birthday?
对 你要喝什么吗?
Yes You want something to drink?
那是什么时候的事? 好几年前啰
When was this? Oh, so many years ago.
贝利先生圣诞节去渡假一星期
Mr. Belli was away for Christmas Gone for a week.
黄道带打来要找贝利先生
The Zodiac called, wanting to talk to him.
我说他人不在家
I said," He is not here."
他说"今天我生日 我要杀人"
He said," I have to kill Today is my birthday."
然后就挂了电话
And then he hangs up.
之后信件就寄来了
Then the letter arrived.
电话是12月20日 信寄来之前打的?
So, the call came before the letter of December 20th.
贝利先生去渡假一个星期?
Mr. Belli was gone for a week?
圣诞节当天才回来 那天不适合工作
He came back on Christmas Not a good day to work.
那他就是18号离开的
So, he left on the 18th.
我有帮到忙吗? 她说那天是他的生日
Is that helpful? She said it was his birthday.
现在你就得去证实了 我该怎么做?
Well, you'd have to confirm that, now wouldn't you? How?
我没有问过她话 也许我搭档有
Well, I never spoke to her, but maybe my partner did.
我要怎么联络你搭档? 没办法 他不想再扯进来
How do I get a hold of him? You don't Bill wanted out of this.
我也觉得他应该抽身
As far as I'm concerned, he should stay out.
那我该如何确认?
How do I confirm it?
假如我搭档跟司法部提过此事
Well, if my partner did talk to someone from Justice
他们应该有报告 这是正常程序
then they would've had to put that in a report That's standard procedure.
好吧 是倪梅尔
Okay Mel Nicolai.
谢谢 再见
Thank you Goodbye.
我只要确认一个日期 葛先生 日期是在12月18到20日之间
I just need to confirm a date Mr. Graysmith... I've narrowed it down between the 18th and the 20th of December, and I just need...
好吧 我参一脚 假设真的有这通电话
Okay, I'll play Let's say this phone call did take place.
而且是黄道带本人打的 他为什么愿意说出自己的生日?
Let's say it really was Zodiac Why would he volunteer the day he was born?
而且12月18日没有人遇害
Plus, nobody died on December 18th
就像他扬言要在周末 杀死一打人一样
just like nobody died over the weekend when he was gonna kill a dozen people
炸毁校车或射杀学童也没发生
or when he was gonna shoot school kids or blow up buses.
葛先生 他是个骗子 也许他犯了错
He's a liar, Mr. Graysmith What if he made a mistake?
如果他没说谎 电话也是他打的 只是没料到接电话的是个好人
What if he wasn't lying? What if it was him on the phone? He didn't expect to pick it up, a nice person to pick up.
这么多也许?
What if? What if? What if?
老实说 比尔查过这条线索
Look, off the record, Bill Armstrong checked this out.
我们很重视这条线索
We took this very seriously.
没有一个嫌犯的生日符合
None of the suspects had the same birthday as this phantom caller.
比尔·阿姆斯壮
Bill Armstrong.
我给你一个建议 你的搜查方向错了
Can I give you a piece of advice? You're looking in the wrong place.
笔迹和指纹才是实实在在的证据
Handwriting, fingerprints, that's what this whole thing's about.
去找这些证据
Stick to the evidence.
嘿
Hi.
今天还好吗? 很累
Hey How was your day? Long.
莫瑞尔是谁?
Who's Sherwood Morrill?
他是位出色的笔迹鉴定专家
He's a handwriting expert in Sacramento.
他打来说明天早上七点能见你
He called He said he can meet you tomorrow morning at 7:00.
太好了
Oh, great.
你早上会请假? 一个小时吧
So you're taking off work? Just an hour.
到沙加缅度要两个小时
Sacramento's two hours away.
真的吗? 真的
Really? Yes.
这是什么?
What's this?
这是 一篇文章
Oh, that's that article.
"罗伯葛雷和出版社 洽谈黄道带一书"
"Robert Graysmith has quietly been shopping his book about the Zodiac."
是啊
Yeah.
文章都是你搜集黄道带的资料 这就是这篇文章的题材
It talks all about you researching Zodiac Well, that's what the article's about.
这种事我并不想让人知道
I'm not so sure that's something we want people to know about.
怎么 你觉得很丢脸?
Why? Are you embarrassed?
罗伯 我们都知道黄道带会做什么?
Robert, what's the one thing we know about Zodiac?
他会看 旧金山纪事报
He reads the Chronicle.
但是他从来不看贺伯·肯恩的专栏
Yeah, but he's never gonna read Herb Caen.
喂? 葛先生?
Hello Mr. Graysmith?
你是今天文章里提到的罗伯?
The Robert Graysmith mentioned in the paper today?
对 我能告诉你谁是黄道带
Yeah? I can tell you who the Zodiac is.
你是谁? 黄道带对电影很着迷
Who is this? The Zodiac Killer is obsessed with movies.
他会拍下他的犯案过程
He recorded his murders on film.
我告诉警方 他们不想调查
I tried to tell the police, but they wouldn't follow through on it.
你要找一个叫鲍伯·冯恩的人
There's a man you need to find His name is Bob Vaughn.
笔! 冯 恩
Pen, pen V A U G H N.
他是黄道带的朋友
He's a friend of the Zodiac's.
冯先生不知道他朋友是凶手
Mr. Vaughn does not know his friend is a killer
他替他保存影片胶卷盒
and he is storing some film canisters for him.
那些影片就是证据
In these canisters is the evidence.
朋友? 这位朋友是谁?
Okay, yeah, friend? Who is this friend?
你有这些资料应该就够了 拜托
You have quite enough to get started Oh, please.
黄道带的名字是瑞克·马修
The Zodiac's name is Rick Marshall.
你的吐司烤焦了
Your toast is burning.
我们在成长的阶段 会习惯每个字母的写法
We choose at some point in our lives how to physically construct each letter.
我们的脑海会牢记这些写法
Once we lock that into our brains
笔迹可能会随着岁月改变
our handwriting may change over the years
但是写字的方法不会变 你懂吗?
but the moves themselves remain unaltered.
我懂
Understand? Yes.
但是黄道带的写法会变
Except Zodiac's doesn't.
尤其是K这个字母
Specifically with his" K."
他第一封信的K用了两笔划
In his first letters, he executed the" K" with two strokes.
之后的信却变成三笔划 为什么?
Later letters, he did them with three.
我们不知道 抱歉 我得浇花
Why? We don't know Excuse me, I've got to spray this.
几个人因为笔迹被排除嫌疑?
How many suspects were cleared through handwriting?
全部 还有计程车上的指纹 全都不符合任何人
All of them Also the print in the cab No match was ever found.
有人能够骗过笔迹检验比对吗?
Is there any way that someone could beat a handwriting test?
没有 不管黄道带是谁 绝对不是我排除嫌疑的那些人
No Whoever the Zodiac is, he's not someone I cleared.
一个月前有个男人找到我家 他看来很烦恼
About a month ago, a man showed up on my doorstep very distraught.
他叫瓦勒斯·佩尼
His name was Wallace Penny.
他说他认识黄道带 还给了名字
He said he knew who the Zodiac was Gave me a name.
瑞克 瑞克什么的 瑞克·马修?
Rick Rick somebody.
是啊 同一个人也打了电话给我
Rick Marshall? Yeah I think that the man who you talked to called me, too.
他一走我就查我的档案 我没排除瑞克·马修的嫌疑
After he left, then I checked my files I never cleared a Rick Marshall.
喂?
Hello?
你是谁?
Hello? Who is this?
打错了
It's the wrong number.
你听过瑞克·马修这名字吗?
Does the name Rick Marshall mean anything to you?
你想找什么? 你有什么?
What are you after? What do you got?
其实你说出了我最爱的嫌犯名字
Hypothetically, you just named my favorite suspect in the whole case.
这些话不能公开 几年前我想采马修的指纹
This is off the record Couple years back, I was trying to get Marshall's prints.
我给他一张照片 他看了一下 还给我的时候说
I handed him a photo He looks at it He's about to give it back and he stops and he says
"天啊 上面都是我的指纹"
"My goodness, I got fingerprints all over this."
然后就把指纹擦掉
And he wipes them off.
你为什么没有比对他的笔迹?
Why didn't you test him for handwriting?
因为后来采到他的指纹
Because when they finally did run his prints
不符合计程车上那枚指纹
they cleared him against the one in Stine's cab.
凶手就不是他 也许是 也许不是
So, then, it's not him Maybe yes, maybe no.
什么意思?
No What do you mean?
黄道带在现场留下一对手套
Zodiac left gloves behind at the scene.
如果他知道要戴手套犯案
If he had the foresight to bring gloves with him
怎么会不小心留下指纹?
how the hell's he gonna accidentally leave a print behind?
指纹印在死者的血迹上面
But it was in the victim's blood.
也许是旁观者的指纹 或是刑警不小心留下的指纹
Could have been one of the bystanders, or a cop just reaches out, boom, false print.
这枚指纹排除了2500名嫌犯
Yeah, but that print disqualified 2500 suspects.
所以才同时比对笔迹 除了瑞克·马修
Which is why we also used handwriting But not for Rick Marshall.
旧金山刑警在他家窗户看到字迹
SFPD saw a handwritten sign in the window of his house.
觉得不像黄道带的笔迹 于是就不去管他了
Decided it looked nothing like the Z letters, so they just moved on.
他们怎么知道那是瑞克的字迹
How do they know that Rick Marshall wrote the sign?
我也这么想
My thoughts exactly.
瑞克·马修是个海军 接受过编码训练
Rick Marshall was a Navy man He received code training.
他也在一家电影院当放映师
He was also a projectionist at a silent film theater.
那我该怎么拿到瑞克的笔迹?
Well, then, how do I get copies of Rick Marshall's handwriting?
三种方法 一 申请搜查令 你拿不到
Three ways One, get a warrant, which you can't.
第二是他自愿提供 不可能 第三种方法呢?
Two, get him to volunteer, which he won't Yeah, and three?
你自己想办法啰
Get creative.
我没有好建议 你拿到我就比对
I don't know what to tell you You get it, I'll analyze it.
其它的就要靠你自己 那个去找你的人
Beyond that, you're on your own Okay, what about the guy who came to see you
也是打给我的那个人呢?
the one who called me?
你是说瓦勒斯·佩尼?
You mean Wallace Penny?
他有留下电话号码吗?
Yeah Did he leave a number?
喂? 嗨 我是罗伯·葛雷史密斯
Hello? Hi, this is Robert Graysmith.
你怎么找到我? 我需要瑞克·马修的笔迹样本
How did you find me? I need a sample of Rick Marshall's handwriting.
我说过 冯恩
I told you Vaughn is who...
佩尼先生 如果瑞克是黄道带
Mr. Penny, if Rick Marshall is the Zodiac
我就需要他的笔迹当证据
I need a sample of his handwriting to confirm it.
你到底能不能帮忙?
Can you help me or not?
瑞克替冯恩工作的电影院
Rick used to draw movie posters for the theater Vaughn worked at.
画过一些海报 我会寄一张给你 谢谢
I'll send one down Thank you.
我需要更多样本 好 但他是吗?
I'll need to see more samples Yeah, but is it...
这是我目前看过最接近的 我们必须小心行事
It's as close as I've ever seen We have to tread lightly here.
我们要指认的这个人是黄道带
We're talking about implicating this man as the Zodiac.
我能拿到更多样本 只要找到冯恩就能找到琳达
I can get more I'll just find Vaughn and I'll track down Linda.
我是说 琳达是黛琳的姐姐 我去过监理处
I mean, Linda is Darlene's sister I've been to the DMV, and I talked to her parents
跟她父母谈过 不过没有人知道她在哪里
but still, nobody knows where to find her.
葛先生 大部分的字迹都符合
Mr. Graysmith, most of the writing matches the exemplar.
不过我最怕的是不符合的部分
In a way, though, it's the part that doesn't match that scares me the most.
什么意思?
What do you mean? Well, on the poster
电影海报上唯一不符合的字母
the one letter that absolutely, positively does not match
就是K
is the letter" K."
你没有卡通动物饼干吧?
You wouldn't happen to have any animal crackers in there, would you?
第五小组 请陶希打回总部
Unit Five Toschi needs to call in on a landline.
1978年4月25日 加州 旧金山
勤务中心 大卫·陶希
Dispatch Hey Dave Toschi.
我帮你接
I'll connect you.
大卫 什么事?
Dave? Yeah What's up?
旧金山纪事报 的达菲·詹宁在总部
Jennings here from the Chronicle.
早上寄来的 你最好看看
It came in this morning and you need to see it right now.
看什么?
See what?
黄道带的信 上面提到你
The new Zodiac letter And it mentions you.
好吧
Okay, okay.
好吧 快回总部
Shit All right, come on Hall of Justice!
快点 快 快
Now! Come on, come on, come on, come on, come on!
大卫
Dave!
你有带在身上吗?
Do you have it with you?
我是黄道带 我回来了
"This is the Zodiac speaking I'm back with you.
告诉贺伯我还在 一直都在
"Tell Herb Caen I am here, I have always been here.
陶希很有一套 不过我更聪明
"That city pig Toschi is good, but I am smarter and better.
他迟早会累了 然后放过我
"He will get tired, then leave me alone.
我等着有人把我拍成电影 谁会饰演我呢?
"I'm waiting for a good movie about me Who will play me?
现在由我掌控局面
"I'm now in control of all things."
他们来自风纪组
These guys are from Internal Affairs.
我们得谈谈
We need to talk.
今晚新闻头条
Good evening Our top story tonight
旧金山警局证实
the San Francisco Police Department has confirmed
自称黄道带并吓坏湾区的凶手 51个月后打破沉默
that the man who calls himself the Zodiac and terrorized the Bay Area has broken his silence of 51 months.
他在信中提到" 我回来了"
In a letter claiming," I am back with you"
但是并没有刻意威胁市民
the Zodiac makes no overt threats against the citizenry
反而想把他的故事拍成电影
and muses that his life and times would make the best movie script yet.
红萝卜很好吃
These carrots are perfect The terse 66 word message also manages...
去看吧 信中还提到 旧金山纪事报  专栏作家贺伯
Just go ...to mention San Francisco Chronicle columnist Herb Caen
和大卫陶希警探
and the Department's own David Toschi by name.
我也可以去吗?
May I be excused? Are they targets?
好 不过你得回来吃完一半晚餐
Fine, but you have to come back and finish at least half of what's on that plate.
我们有更多密码杀手的报导
More team coverage on the cipher slayer's return...
镜头交给艾伦佛列曼
Okay? Okay ...begins as Alan Freeman has more.
谢谢你 艾瑞克 旧金山纪事报 专栏作家莫宝
Thank you, Eric San Francisco Chronicle columnist Armistead Maupin says
认为这封信是伪造的
that he thinks not only is this new letter a forgery
而伪造这封信的人 就是长年追捕黄道带的警探 大卫·陶希
but it was written by the very man trusted to hunt down this killer, David Toschi.
莫宝这位非常受尊重的作家
Maupin, a very well respected author, has gone on record saying
公开表示他相信陶希伪造这封信 是为了引人注意
that he believes Toschi wrote the letter to drum up publicity for himself.
莫宝把大卫写成他专栏的角色
Maupin used David as a character in his column.
大卫觉得很过瘾 于是匿名写信
David got a kick out of it and so he wrote a couple of anonymous letters
请莫宝继续写这个角色
asking for the character to be brought back.
就像假装粉丝写信给自己而已
It was like writing fan mail to himself That's all.
不过那封信不是大卫写的
But David did not write that letter.
我相信不是他 应该也不会有什么影响
No, I'm sure that he didn't And I'm sure that this will all blow over.
不会有影响?
Blow over?
他被踢出重案组
They kicked him out of Homicide.
他们甚至逼他像罪犯留下笔迹
They made him give his handwriting like some common criminal.
我能跟他谈谈吗? 不行
May I talk to him? No.
请你问他有没有调查过 一个叫瑞克·马修的人
Okay, can you just ask him if he ever investigated a man named Rick Marshall?
你满脑子只有这个案子吗?
Is that all you can think about?
葛先生 莫宝在你的报社工作
Mr. Graysmith, Maupin works at your paper We trust...
这女孩想要修音乐课? 大卫
This girl, she wants music lessons? Dave! Dave!
我待会儿再找你
I'll catch up to you.
别再打到我家 懂吗?
You stop calling my house Do you understand me?
我只要你帮我找到琳达
I just need your help to find Linda.
老天爷 一下子就好
Jesus Look, two seconds.
听着 我们做过一些笔迹比对
Look, we've been running handwriting samples.
"我们"是谁? 我和莫瑞尔
Who's we? Sherwood and I.
莫瑞尔? 他被鉴识组开除后
Sherwood? Sherwood who was fired from Questioned Documents?
他和保罗一样变成酒鬼 他退休了
Sherwood who drinks like Paul Avery now?
他这么跟你说吗?
He retired Is that what he told you?
你是说他错了吗? 我是说别再打到我家
What, are you saying he's wrong? I'm saying stop calling my house.
我们比对瑞克·马修的笔迹 不 罗伯
We ran them on Rick Marshall No, Robert.
我知道你认为不是他 我只知道我不想再说下去
No, I know you don't think it's him I mean, no, I am not having this conversation.
我找不到梅休或琳达
But I think that Marshall knew Darlene, and I can't talk to Mageau or Linda, so I'm gonna talk to Bob Vaughn.
罗伯 闭嘴
Robert Robert, stop it! What?
你再调查下去会筋疲力尽 也会走进死胡同
Okay, the Rick Marshalls of this world will suck you dry They're blind alleys.
黄道带说他不会公布他的对象 他只会直接杀人
But he said he wasn't gonna announce his murders anymore, Dave He was just gonna do them.
你知道逮到他的机率有多小?
Do you know what the chances of us arresting someone are now?
而且时间过了这么久 很多证物都遗失
Too much time has gone by, okay? Too much of the evidence is lost.
证人也老了 忘记很多事
People get old, Robert They forget.
我当了25年警察 12年凶案警探
Now, I have been a cop for 25 years Murder police for 12.
你靠什么维生? 你明明知道
What do you do for a living? You know what I do for a living.
你是个漫画家 你想说什么?
You're a cartoonist So what are you saying?
逮捕黄道带是我的工作 不是你的
I am saying Zodiac was my job It is not yours.
他还在逍遥法外 大卫 我不管这个案子了
He's still out there, Dave No, Robert I am through with this.
也跟你没关系了
I am through with you.
1970年9月24日呢?
What about September 26, 1970?
那是哪一起命案? 太浩湖护士失踪
Okay, which one was that? The Lake Tahoe nurse goes missing.
春分点的前一天 爸? 画个记号
One day before the vernal equinox Dad? Yeah Mark that.
还有1971年6月19日
Got another one June 19th, 1971.
一定很接近夏至
That's got to be near the summer solstice.
大伙儿 别告诉妈妈这件事哦
Oh, guys Don't tell Mom about our special project, okay?
你跟妈为什么不一起睡?
How come you and Mom don't sleep in the same bed anymore?
葛先生 我是那帕警局的肯恩
Hello Mr. Graysmith, it's Ken Narlow from Napa.
你好 警官 谢谢你回电
Oh, Captain Narlow Thank you for calling me back.
我能帮什么忙?
Yeah How can I help?
我们交叉比对月亮周期
I called you because we've been cross referencing lunar cycles
和黄道带凶杀案的时间表
with the Zodiac's timeline.
1969年以后 月亮周期一开始 就有一起命案
More often than not, each cycle since '69 corresponds with an attack
和一封信 或是未破解的谋杀案
or with one of the letters, or an unsolved homicide.
谁跟你调查这件事? 我的同事
Who's working with you on this? Some colleagues.
爸?
Dad?
请你稍等一下 爸?
Ken, can you hold on one second? Dad?
什么事? 这是什么?
What is it? What's this?
收到黄道带最后信件的十年间
In the decade since the Zodiac's last cipher was received
每个联邦单位都想破解密码
every federal agency has taken a crack at decoding it.
在这些单位都失败之后 一名漫画家却成功破解密码
But today, where those agencies had failed, a cartoonist has succeeded.
你是怎么办到的?
How did you do it?
参考图书馆的大量书籍 我也喜欢解码 我就
Oh, just a lot of books from the library, and I love puzzles, so I just...
液 臭图书馆
Yeah, the fucking library.
只要努力就一定能成功
I believe that you can accomplish anything that you put your mind...
J字开头? 女子监狱?
That's a" J"? Okay Honor Camp?
谢谢你
Thank you so much.
找到琳达了 她在坐牢 很棒吧
Hey, we found Linda She's in jail Isn't that great?
你为什么要这样? 她会指认瑞克
Why'd you do it? Because she'll be able to identify Rick...
你在说什么? 你上了电视
What are you talking about? You went on TV.
你让他认得你的长相 老婆 你太紧张了
You put yourself out there for him to see Oh, hon, you're being paranoid.
那是谁每周半夜打到家里来的?
Oh, hon, you're being paranoid The who's been calling our house in the middle of the night?
谁也不是
Nobody.
你要怎样才肯罢休? 现在不能谈
What's it gonna take for you to be done with this?
我得去见鲍伯·冯恩
I can't talk about this now I have to go see Bob Vaughn.
不行 我们现在就要谈
Well, that's too bad, because we're gonna talk about this.
你几时才会罢手? 等你找到他 逮捕他?
And when is it gonna be finished? When you catch him? When you arrest him?
严肃一点 我是很严肃
Be serious I am serious.
我得知道他究竟是谁
I need to know who he is.
我得站在他面前 看着他的眼睛 知道他就是黄道带
I need to stand there, I need to look him in the eye and I need to know that it's him.
这比你家人的安危更重要?
Is that more important than your family's safety?
当然不是
Of course not.
为什么? 你为什么要这么做?
Why? Why do you need to do this?
为什么?
Why?
因为没有人肯做
Because nobody else will.
这理由不够好
That's not good enough.
说完了吗? 我能走了吗?
Are you done? Can I go?
冯先生? 葛先生?
Mr. Vaughn? Mr. Graysmith?
是的 嗨 你要找我谈?
Yes Hi You needed to speak to me?
对 街角有一家咖啡馆
Yes There's a coffee shop right on the corner.
不如到我家 我不想麻烦你
Why don't we just go to my home? Oh, I don't wanna put you out.
一点也不会 你停在哪儿? 就在那里
It's no trouble at all Where are you parked? Just right there.
跟着我的车 好吧
You can follow me Oh Okay.
小心台阶
Watch your step Come in.
很棒的房子 谢谢
Very nice house Oh, thank you.
感觉很简朴
It's very rustic.
夹克可以给我吗? 不用 谢谢 我很好
Can I take your jacket? No, thank you, I'm fine.
那就这边请
Okay This way, please.
请坐 谢谢
Have a seat Thank you.
喝点茶吗? 不用了
How about some tea? Oh, no, I'm all right.
你确定? 确定
You sure? Yes.
我想问你关于一部电影
I wanted to ask you about a film that the Avenue may have played
你在电影院当琴师时放过的电影 最危险的游戏
while you were the organist there The Most Dangerous Game?
那是经典电影 1932年
Oh, it's a classic R KO 1932.
费芮 乔麦克雷 莱斯里班克斯 我们放映了很多次
Fay Wray, Joel McCrea, Leslie Banks We've run that picture many times.
是68还是69年?
In '68, '69?
我得查查记录 怎么了?
I'd have to check my records Why?
你记得黄道带吗?
Do you remember the Zodiac?
你想问瑞克·马修 是吧?
This is about Rick Marshall, isn't it?
他曾是那里的放映师 对吗? 有一段时间
He was a projectionist there, right? For a time, yes.
但是我没跟他保持连络
But I have no occasion to correspond with him these days.
好 黄道带有一次杀人时
Okay Well, there is a connection
跟那部电影有关联
between one of the Zodiac attacks and that film.
你是说那个符号?
You mean the symbol?
等等
Hold on.
黄道带的符号 出现在片头的倒数胶卷
The Zodiac symbol on film It's on the countdown.
每次放映前都会剪掉
It's trimmed off each reel before it's shown
不过影片送来的时候都会在
but it always arrives with it.
就在这里
Right there.
我第一次在报上看到时就想到了
The first time I saw it in the papers, I thought about that.
我们收到线报
We got a tip
瑞克留了一个胶卷盒给你 还交代你不要打开
that Rick left a film canister here that he told you never to open.
关于神秘的影片胶卷盒线报
A tip about a mysterious film canister?
是真的吗?
Is it true?
是真的
Yes.
你有打开过吗? 没有
Did you open it? No.
我能看看吗? 瑞克在1972年拿回去了
May I see it? Rick took it back in 1972.
这条线报让你联想到  瑞克就是黄道带?
This tip is how you got it in your head that Rick is the Zodiac?
胶卷盒以及海报
That and the poster.
海报?
The poster?
瑞克画的那张海报
The poster that Rick drew.
上面的笔迹是最接近嫌犯的笔迹
The handwriting is the closest that we have ever come to a match.
海报不是瑞克画的 不 他画了这张
Rick didn't draw any posters No, he drew this one.
葛先生 海报是我亲笔画的
Mr. Graysmith, I do the posters myself.
那是我的笔迹
That's my handwriting.
我 我不想再占用你的时间了
I won't take any more of your time.
我去看是哪一年放映这部电影的
Why don't I just go and find out when we played that film?
不用了
Oh, that's all right.
没关系 就在地下室
It's not a problem They're just down in the basement.
加州不是每个人都有地下室
Not many people have basements in California.
我就有
I do.
你要来吗 葛先生?
You coming, Mr. Graysmith?
原版的海报我全都自己保留
The original studio one sheets, I always kept for myself.
你带来的那张便宜货
The cheapo knock offs like you brought today
我会糅成一团丢到后巷
I end up tossing into the back alley.
69年
'69.
你一个人住吗?
You live alone?
最危险的游戏 1969年5月放映
Most Dangerous Game ran in May '69.
那大概是黄道带 寄出第一封信九星期前 对吧?
So, that would be about nine weeks before the first Zodiac letter, correct?
对
Yeah.
你认为他在戏院中看过那部电影后 受到启发?
Do you think he saw the film in our theater and was inspired?
你确定屋里没有别人?
Are you sure there's nobody else in the house?
你想上楼去看吗?
Would you like to go upstairs and check?
不了
No.
谢谢 非常谢谢你
Thank you Thanks for everything.
不用客气
You're welcome.
大门锁住了
It's locked.
谢谢你
Thank you.
晚安 葛先生
Good night, Mr. Graysmith!
一定有两个凶手 其中一个
Two killers Got to be two killers One has the...
孩子们?
Guys?
我带孩子到我妈家 别打来
琳达 戴布诺 桑瓦昆监狱
你有五分钟的时间
You've got five minutes.
琳达?
Linda?
我是罗伯
Hi, I'm Robert.
你收到我的信吗?
Did you get my note?
是什么事? 黄道带
What's this about? Zodiac.
我猜也是
Figures.
你看起来有那种样子 什么样子?
You got the look What look?
我没别的意思
I didn't mean anything.
告诉我关于那场油漆派对
Tell me about this painting party.
我很久前就跟条子说过
I told the cops about that so long ago.
男人总是围绕着黛琳 就算是婚后也一样
Darlene always had a lot of boys around, even though she was married.
其中有一个很怪
And this one guy was weird, though.
他常从提华纳带礼物给她
He used to bring her presents from Tijuana and...
我也不知道她干嘛跟他交朋友
I don't know why she was friends with him.
不过她说他杀过人
She once told me he'd killed somebody.
真的吗?
Really?
好像是他在当兵的时候
Yeah, I think maybe when he was in the service.
海军? 应该是吧
Navy? I think so.
他喜欢电影? 他是影痴吗?
Was he into movies? Was he a movie buff?
我只知道他对人没兴趣
I can tell you that he was not into people.
黛琳办的那个派对 只是请大家来喝酒 帮忙油漆
The party Darlene threw, people were supposed to just show up and drink beer, help paint.
这家伙却穿了套西装
But this guy showed up in a suit
一个人整晚坐在椅子上
and just sat in a chair all by himself all night long.
也没跟任何人讲话
Didn't talk to anyone.
黛琳叫我离他远一点 她很怕他
And Darlene told me to stay away from him She was scared of him.
几星期后她就死了
And a couple of weeks later, she was dead.
很遗憾 你知道他的名字吗?
I'm sorry Do you remember his name?
有点像绰号 好像是史丹
I mean, it was short, like a nickname, like Stan.
瑞克? 不 我想不是
Rick? No, I don't think so.
你确定吗? 确定
Are you sure? Yeah.
那么久了 你怎么能确定? 用力想
How can you be sure? It was a long time ago Think hard.
我很用力在想
I am thinking hard.
是瑞克
It was Rick.
不 不是 是瑞克 瑞克·马修
No, it wasn't It was Rick It was Rick Marshall No.
不是 快说是
Just say it!
他不是瑞克
It wasn't Rick.
是李
It was Leigh.
李? 是啊 李
Leigh? Yeah, Leigh.
听起来没错
Sounds right.
警官! 你得让我进去
Officer! I need you to let me in.
是紧急事件吗? 我只要看一份档案
Is this an emergency? No, I just need to see one file.
明早再来 一份档案 只要一下子
No, you need to come back tomorrow morning One file, just for one second 8:00 a.m , when we're open.
穆拉斯队长!
Sergeant! Sergeant Mulanax!
我只要看一份档案 五分钟
Sergeant, I just need to see one file!
我知道档案在哪里
Just give me five minutes I know exactly where it is.
拜托
Please!
我不应该跟你说话
I shouldn't be talking to you.
你只有五分钟 好
You got five minutes Okay.
就是这里
Here Here.
琳达说她的好朋友包括李
Linda states that some of Darlene's closest friends are Leigh
常从提华纳带礼物给她
who used to bring Darlene presents from Tijuana.
又怎样? 他认识她
So what? He knew her.
琳达提到李
Linda said Leigh This is Leigh.
这只是几百个名字的其中一个 不算什么
No That's just one name in a file that contains hundreds It's nothing.
大卫·陶希  他也同意我说的
Dave Toschi... Agrees with me.
这项调查到此为止
Our investigation into this subject is over.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
喂?
Hello.
谁在那里?
Who's there?
你没回我电话 我有点忙
You didn't return my calls Oh, I've been kind of busy.
是啊 看得出来
Yeah I can see that.
书写得怎样?
How's the book coming?
我试着寄这些给你
I tried to send you these.
我打给了报社
I called the Chron.
我不再是那里的漫画家了
Well, I'm not a cartoonist anymore, so...
我听说了
I heard.
你最后一次吃过东西是在什么时候?
When's the last time you ate something?
一切都没有意义了
Nothing makes sense anymore.
有过意义吗? 有 曾经有
Did it ever? Yeah, it did.
罗伯 那只是一次约会 并没有结束
Robert, it was just the date that didn't end.
你真的这么想?
You don't mean that.
有一点
A little.
孩子们很想你
The kids miss you.
我不能让他们看到我这样 我也不想 把你认为该做的事做完
I can't have them see me like this Neither can I So, do whatever you have to
把这本书写完
but finish this.
葛雷的副本
亚瑟·李·艾伦 生日12 18 33
大卫
Dave!
大卫 是我罗伯
Dave! It's Robert!
大卫 他真跑来了?
Dave! Is he actually here?
我要杀了他
I'm gonna kill him.
我要报警 我的枪呢?
I'm calling SFPD Where's my gun?
大卫 罗伯 快滚开
Dave! Robert! Go away!
大卫 他犯了一个错 离开窗户
Dave! He made a mistake! Get away from the window I'll meet you around front.
我到前门 不行
No, you won't.
你得听听这个 不 我不听
You have to hear this! No, I don't, Robert!
他只有在生日那天最脆弱
The birthday was the one time that he was weak!
也是唯一一次泄漏身分
The one time that he gave something away!
罗伯 我要报警了 是亚瑟·李·艾伦
Robert, I am calling the police It's Arthur Leigh Allen!
你那名字哪里来的?
Where did you get that name?
他打到贝利家 69年12月 说" 今天我生日 我非得杀人不可"
He called the Bellis' house December '69" I need to kill Today's my birthday."
那天是他的生日
It was his birthday.
亚瑟·李·艾伦的生日是12月18日
Arthur Leigh Allen was born on December 18th.
进来
Get in here.
拿去 谢了
Here you go Thanks.
他写信给我 你知道吗?
He wrote me, you know?
2500名嫌犯 唯一写信给我的就是李·艾伦
2500 suspects, the only one who ever wrote me a letter was Leigh Allen.
有时候嫌犯想帮忙 我知道 罗伯
They like to help, you know, sometimes Yes, Robert, I know.
他在1975年1月因性骚扰被捕
He was arrested January 1975 for molestation.
一出狱就寄信给我
He sent me that when he got out.
亲爱的大卫 需要帮忙就告诉我
"Dear Dave, if I can ever be of any help to you, just let me know.
抱歉我不是凶手 而信件是用打的
"I'm sorry I wasn't your man." And it's typewritten.
打字并不算犯法
Using a typewriter is not a crime.
他也认识黛琳
And he knew Darlene.
这是瓦列霍的档案
It's in the Vallejo files.
穆拉斯说他是你的头号嫌犯
Mulanax said that he was your favorite suspect.
你花两年时间调查他 而且没人比你更接近破案
That you spent two years on him, and that nobody ever came close.
所有的证据都说不是他
All the evidence said no.
莫瑞尔说他的笔迹不符合
Sherwood disqualified his handwriting.
那个和保罗一样满嘴酒味的莫瑞尔?
The same Sherwood that drinks like Paul Avery now?
是的 莫瑞尔写说这不是嫌犯的笔迹 泰瑞也能鉴定
Yes, you have Sherwood Morrill in writing saying," I'm sorry, this just won't work."
他的徒弟 就算他只是徒弟
But you also have Terry Pascoe... His protégé Yeah, fine, it's his protégé
好歹他也是专家 他说
but he's a handwriting expert nonetheless, and he's saying
"别以笔迹排除掉这名嫌犯"
"Do not disqualify this suspect on the basis of handwriting."
所以两名专家意见不同
So the two cancel each other out No, they don't.
不 这是莫瑞尔的案子 他也曾是鉴识组组长
It was Sherwood's case He was the head of Questioned Documents.
假如案子上了法庭 辩方会让莫瑞尔证明李艾伦没罪
If it went to trial, all the defense would have to do is call Sherwood to the stand.
我们也没办法把艾伦告上法庭 因为根本没有证据
And there was no way of getting Allen into court in the first place, because there was no evidence, Robert.
怎么会没有证据? 你看过他的密码
What do you mean, there's no evidence? You have him seen with the ciphers.
军用长靴和手套的尺寸符合
The military boot prints The same size shoes and gloves.
最危险的游戏 黄道带手表 他当过小学老师
The Most Dangerous Game The Zodiac watch The background with school children.
圣诞节拼错 沾血凶刀 这些都是间接证据
The misspellings of Christ mass The bloody knives All circumstantial.
保罗·史坦的衬衫 钱包 钥匙
Paul Stine's shirt, his wallet, his keys.
在拖车屋里都没有找到
We should have found one of those things in that trailer We didn't That's...
凯萨琳说李星期五下班后
Okay Catherine Allen states that" Leigh cleaned out his trailer on Friday after work
就把拖车屋清空搬到圣塔罗莎 1971年8月7日 星期六
"and moved it to Santa Rosa on Saturday, August 7th, 1971."
你是在8月4日 到炼油厂问他话的
You interviewed him at the refinery on August 4th Yeah So, he's cleaning out his trailer
然后48小时之后 他就匆匆搬到另一个城市?
he's moving into a different county 48 hours after you interviewed him?
让我们一对一比对他们的行踪 好  好吧 好吧
Okay Okay Look at the stuff side by side, Dave All right.
亚瑟·李·艾伦和黄道带的行踪
Okay, Arthur Leigh Allen and the Zodiac, their timelines.
第一起瓦列霍命案是几时? 1968年圣诞节
When was the first murder in Vallejo? Christmas, 1968.
8个月前艾伦 因骚扰学童被开除
Eight months before that, Allen is fired for molesting his students
家人发现他有恋童癖
and his family discovers that he's a pedophile.
第一封信几时寄到? 69年7月
Now, when do the letters begin? July, '69.
那是在黛琳费伦的命案之后
After the murder of Darlene Ferrin.
他一直寄信 直到你去上班的地方找他
And they continue until you go to see him at work.
后来的信 还有没有史坦的沾血衬衫?
Now, after that, do any of the letters contain swatches of Paul Stine's shirt?
没有 因为他害怕 把衬衫丢了 他知道你盯上他
No Because he dumped them, because he got scared Because he knew that you were on to him.
黄道带的下一封信几时出现? 一直等到1974年1月
So, when's the next letter from Zodiac? Not until January of 1974.
他整整沉默了三年
He is silent for three years.
到了74年他才安心 因为大家都排除艾伦的嫌疑
Then, in '74, he feels comfortable again because everybody's moved off Allen as a suspect.
接着我们陆续收到黄道带的三封信 74年1月 5月 7月
And what do we get? Three new letters from Zodiac in January, May, and July in '74.
然后又没再收到信了 艾伦发生什么事?
But then the letters stop What happens to Allen?
他被逮捕了
He's arrested.
1975年1月 他被送到阿塔斯卡戴罗监狱
January, 1975, they send him to Atascadero.
那段期间黄道带没有寄一封信
We don't get another letter from Zodiac the entire time he's there.
他几时被放出来的? 1977年8月
When is he released? August, '77.
艾伦出狱 打了一封抱歉信 然后呢?
Allen gets out He types you an apology, and then what?
四年来首次接到黄道带的信件
We get our first new Zodiac letter in four years.
所以 黄道带应该认识黛琳 对吧?
Okay Zodiac had to have known Darlene Ferrin, right?
对 因为她被杀那天晚上的通联纪录
Yes, because of the phone calls on the night of her murder.
因为透过瓦列霍档案纪录 我们知道黛琳认识一名男子叫李
Because of the Vallejo file, we know that Darlene knew a man named Leigh?
没错 因此撇开所有的巧合 罗伯
Yes So, all coincidence aside, Robert
你如何确定这两人是同一个李
how can you be sure that Leigh Allen is the Leigh from this file?
瓦列霍虽然是小镇 但也不太小 你怎么把这两个人凑在一块?
Now, Vallejo is a small town, but it's not that small How do you put the two of them together?
这是一个涵盖南北加州的案件
This is a case that's covered both Northern and Southern California
嫌犯与被害人相隔一百英里
with victims and suspects spread over hundreds of miles.
这你同意吧? 同意
Would you agree? Yes.
黛琳在瓦列霍一家煎饼店工作
Darlene Ferrin worked at the Vallejo House of Pancakes
就在田纳西和凯罗街口
on the corner of Tennessee and Caroll.
亚瑟·李·艾伦 住在费斯诺街母亲家的地下室
Arthur Leigh Allen lived in his mother's basement on Fresno Street.
两栋房子距离不到50码
Door to door, that is less than 50 yards.
这是真的吗?
Is that true?
我实际走过
I've walked it.
老天爷
Jesus Christ.
所以呢?
So?
指纹 笔迹 我不要你以警察的身分回答 但我是个警察啊
The prints, the handwriting... I'm not asking you as a cop But I am a cop.
我无法证实
I can't prove this.
你无法证实不表示不是真的
Just because you can't prove it, doesn't mean it's not true.
别冲动 辣手神探
Easy, Dirty Harry.
完成你的书
Finish the book.
谢谢 谢谢你的早餐
Thank you Thank you for breakfast.
1983年12月20日 加州 瓦列霍
我能效劳吗?
Can I help you?
不用
No.
七年半后 加州 安大略 1991年8月16日
<索命黄道带> 畅销书
梅休先生
Mr. Mageau.
感谢你抽空过来 你就是电话中的那个人?
Thanks for coming to see me You're the one I talked to on the phone?
瓦列霍警局 我是乔治·巴渥 我接手杰克穆拉斯的案子
I'm George Bawart Vallejo PD I took over for Jack Mulanax.
都22年了 我不确定帮得上忙
It's been 22 years I don't know how I can help you.
这是警方的正常程序 我要让你看一些照片
Well, this is just a formality I'm gonna show you a group of photographs.
射伤你的人也许在这些人当中
Now, the person that shot you may or may not be among these photographs.
你不一定要指出任何人 懂吗?
You don't have to pick anybody out just because I'm showing you these pictures, you understand?
我懂 警官
Yes, sir, I do.
好吧
All right.
慢慢来
Take your time.
你认不出任何人也没关系
If you don't recognize anyone, that's okay.
是他
That's him.
你有多确定?
How sure are you?
非常确定
Yeah, I'm pretty sure.
他像这家伙有张圆脸
He had a round face like this guy.
你又指认第二名嫌犯吗?
Wait Am I to understand that you're now identifying the second photograph?
不 我只是说他也有一张圆脸
No, no Just that he had a round face like that.
就是这个人
It's this man.
好吧
All right.
1到10分 10分是最确定
Now, on a scale of one to 10, 10 being positive
你有多确定?
how sure are you?
至少有8分
At least an eight.
我最后一次看到这张脸 是1969年7月4日
The last time I saw this face was July 4th, 1969.
我很确定他是向我开枪的家伙
I am very sure that's the man who shot me.
麦克·梅休指认亚瑟·李·艾伦之后
警方安排了一次会议 打算以多重谋杀罪起诉他
艾伦在会议进行以前 因心脏病发身亡
2002年 艾伦的DNA不符合
33年前黄道带信件采到的样本
旧金山及瓦列霍警方
拒绝根据DNA检验报告 排除艾伦的涉案嫌疑
2004年 旧金山警局
撤销对于黄道带的调查
至今本案在那帕市 索拉诺郡
瓦列霍市仍然开放调查
亚瑟·李·艾伦仍是唯一的主嫌
陶希警探于1989年 从旧金山警局退休
他于1978年被控 伪造黄道带信件一案也被撤销
保罗·艾瑞于2000年12月10日 因肺气肿去世 享年66
他的骨灰由他的家人 撒在旧金山湾
罗伯·葛雷史密斯定居旧金山
和他的小孩维持良好关系
他声称亚瑟·李·艾伦去世之后 就没再接到匿名电话